[Music]
Hello everybody. Good evening. Good day
and welcome back to the Oscar video
show. Today we discuss anything.
I will take your questions from the
super chat and you can ask me absolutely
anything. So before we begin, let's see
who all is there on the live chat. Let's
see.
Avinash Nagananda Shenoy bought gaming
oi oi. Pratham Sharma is back. UMX lol
haha.
Um real painter is here. All right, all
right, sir. Scintillating kids Amandeep
Singh Bidi Tanmay Deshpande GKGS
1 KE good morning. Well, good morning to
you.
Shreyas again Namaste Alvin Rodriguez
has lost his younger brother. I'm so
sorry to hear this, sir.
I am so sorry. I'm so sorry.
Oh, well, that's that's
genuinely terrible. I'm so sorry to hear
this.
Um condolences to you and your family
and may the gods give you the strength
to
yeah, get through this. Very sorry to
hear this.
Um Nagananda Shenoy Sonasan Sanduji
Adesh Shah
Alankrita Das bought gaming
scintillating kids again Vishnu Mohanand
geopolitical Dubai is here from Indore.
Basket Bandit is also here.
Shishir Upadhyay Adesh Shah
uh
Swami is also here. Ganapathy critical
thinker 24 Ayush Singh Namaste.
Um
McLovin 69 is here. Hello. Priyanka
Jawalia good evening. Namaste. Deepika
Mishra hello. Richest Pakistani is here.
Turn on the drums Gal Galmadi
Adwait Ashwini Ayush Kumar Singh once
again the mom.
Animals for laugh is here from Mumbai.
Uh
Urjasvi Namaste Rem 17291 hello.
Priyanka Jawalia once again good
evening. Rahul Himtani is here from
Mumbai.
Hello. Shashank Kaushik Namaskaram
Devanam Priyapriyadarshi is here from
Odisha. Jai Jagannath, sir.
Meet Mistry Pratham Sharma
uh Ayush Anshuman Mohapatra
Mega Indeed Mega.
Uh Chandru
Mr. Jam Raj Rade
um Montu Prajapati
Isaac Newton is here with us. Animals
for laugh once again Sharan Amy Chloe
Namaste.
DJ Divine Joy Hello. S- Spartan 6678906
Reddy is always ready. Good to see you
Reddy, sir.
Uh who else do we have? Adwait Ashwini
Isaac Newton once again Mystic SK Jai
Shri Krishna
Gray from Odisha
uh
Akhir Pasta is here from Jammu. Very
good to have you. Nagananda Shenoy is
here from Hyderabad. Swami says when
will I take the space
session?
How about next week? Yeah?
We can do a space section session next
week.
Okay, let's get going
from
Let's get going with the questions.
Okay, let's go. What What are the
questions in the super chats? All right,
Spartan says if the English hadn't come
to India
would Marathas be the rulers of the
biggest and most substantial portion of
the Indian subcontinent? Maybe a stupid
question but still curious. Well, it's
not a stupid question.
See
the Maratha Empire had uh
defeated the Mughal Empire, right? The
Mughal Empire which which uh
went downhill after the death of uh the
what's his name? Aurangzeb, right? 1707
or 1717. 1707 AD.
And uh the Mughal Empire goes downwards
and the Maratha Empire has this big
upsurge and by the mid-1800s the Maratha
Empire controls much of the Indian
subcontinent.
And then there is in-fighting among the
Marathas. There are internal issues that
cause
the decline of the Maratha Empire rather
rapidly and the English obviously take
advantage of that.
So let's say the English weren't there
in India. What would have happened?
Well, maybe you would have had
fragmented Maratha rule. One Maratha
ruler here, one Maratha ruler there,
another Maratha ruler somewhere else.
That sort of thing.
Because the empire was was on the you
know, uh there was in-fighting. There
were there were issues within it.
So uh empires typically see on average
an empire if you look at uh
the history of India the past 2 and 1/2
thousand years
on average an empire or even a dynasty
it it uh rules for about 2 and 1/2
centuries. If it's a strong
uh kingdom or empire or dynasty. 2 and
1/2 centuries.
Um so the Maratha Empire begins let's
say what? 1750s?
It would have lasted until now, I
suppose.
Yeah, I suppose it would have in some
shape or form or
or something like that.
1750 plus 250 is what? 2000.
Yeah, so it would
possibly
in some shape or form be the be in
control of various parts of the Indian
subcontinent. Maybe different Maratha
rule. If it if it
would not have remained united for
whatever reason because of issues then
maybe you would have had Maratha rulers
in different parts of the country. So
yeah, it could have happened that way.
But as we know, it's all hypothetical
hypothetical because the British the
English took over.
Bhaskar Bandit says at the at Adi
Shankaracharya's time we discussed
Buddhism was at its peak. He restored
Vedic Dharma back. What was happening in
Bharat in terms of cultural cultural
morals ethics code of conduct etc.?
I am not an expert on this
this period of Indian history.
So that's why I generally don't take uh
you know, history super chats because
when it comes to geopolitics you can
answer things based on patterns
based on your understanding of how the
world is right now. When it comes to
history you have to be an expert in all
these different specific portions and
you know, periods of history.
Uh people will ask me about various
dynasties. I don't know about every
dynasty. I haven't studied that.
So I'm not very sure about what was the
deal during Adi Shankaracharya's time.
First of all, we're not quite sure when
was Adi Shankaracharya's time period.
Some people say it is so and so century.
Some people say it's long before that.
But what we know is that during his time
Buddhism was
prevalent across much of India both the
Dharma. How did Buddhism become so
prevalent?
It originated as as this obscure little
branch of Dharma.
That's how Buddhism
you know, originated.
It is our Emperor Ashoka who made it so
prominent.
So without Ashoka's patronage
Buddhism would have remained obscure but
he made it very prominent for political
reasons.
And that's why it became
so widespread across the subcontinent
and beyond.
And
Adi Shankaracharya is is the person who
brought mainstream
Dharma back into the subcontinent and
um his life's work was to ensure the
resurgence
and
and dominance once again of the
mainstream Hindu Dharma.
So what was happening in Bharat in terms
of cultural etc.? It was all Buddhist.
That's what I can tell you but I am not
an expert in this particular period of
history. Uh
so I can't tell you in detail.
Bhaskar Bandit says how did China get
Southern Mongolia, Manchuria, East
Turkestan without resistance from the
big powers?
Most never heard of the latter two which
is Manchuria and East Turkestan only now
on social media.
Well, that's an interesting question.
Did See, first of all we need to
understand the big powers.
Who are the big powers we're talking
about? If we're talking about the early
part of the 20th century, the big powers
are the UK the British Empire.
If we're talking about let's say 1900
around that time
the biggest power is the is the British
Empire. Then you have Russia which is
also a major Eurasian power. Uh China is
is is not in good shape.
And the United States hasn't yet emerged
yet as as a great power.
About 1950
you have the UK has kind of lost ground
significantly. It's on the verge of
becoming a secondary world power. The US
and the USSR are the two great powers
and China is still just about emerging
from civil war. That's 1950.
So
So if you look at Eurasia
the region that we're talking about,
let's go to the map, okay?
Okay, let's start Let's go to the map
and understand which regions we're
discussing.
Excuse me.
See, when we talk about East Turkestan,
it is what the Chinese currently call
the Xinjiang.
Okay?
North of Tibet. That's That is East
Turkestan.
If you talk about
Southern Mongolia
Excuse me.
Uh
Southern Mongolia is is a pretty
self-evident. It is the southern It is
south of what is the current present-day
nation nation-state of Mongolia.
It is almost as large as present-day
Mongolia and it has been absorbed by
China. So that is Southern Mongolia.
Excuse me.
The Chinese call it East Mongolia.
And when it comes to Manchuria
it is this big region north of the
Korean Peninsula and east of Beijing.
And uh
the capital
Excuse me.
So it's the northeast of China
essentially.
So that is Manchuria. So what is the
deal? How did China acquire these
territories? How did China become so
large?
So um
we have to go back a couple of
centuries, maybe more than a couple of
centuries.
When it comes to
Inner Mongolia, the Chinese call it
Inner Mongolia. We can call it Southern
Mongolia.
So China was under
China was conquered by the Mongols.
China was conquered by the great Shri
Chinggis Khan
in uh
the 1200s.
Uh 1220-ish
onwards kind of or maybe slightly before
that. You can look up the exact dates
around that time.
So China was conquered by
Chinggis Khan and Chinggis Khan's
grandson Kublai Khan became the well,
the ruler of China, the emperor of China
and uh
he
founded what's called the Yuan Dynasty,
which was a conquest dynasty, which was
a which was a Mongol dynasty that ruled
that conquered and ruled China.
And eventually
the Chinese now today claim the Yuan
Dynasty as a Chinese dynasty and they
claim that whatever the Yuan Dynasty had
conquered and possessed is Chinese
territory. So that's how they claimed uh
uh Tibet. That's how they claimed uh
Xinjiang. That's how they claimed uh
Southern Mongolia or Inner Mongolia.
But you can claim everything in the
world, that makes no difference unless
you have the capacity, the wherewithal
to grab those territories and hold on to
them.
So uh after the fall of the Yuan
Dynasty, we had other dynasties.
Eventually, we had the Qing Dynasty,
which is a Manchurian Manchu origin
dynasty, which ended in what? 1910 or
around that time.
So the Qing Dynasty uh
came from Manchuria, right? It was a
Manchu Manchu origin dynasty.
And uh
it
at various points in time
it ruled over parts of Southern Mongolia
and East Turkestan.
In the 1850s, you had these big revolts
in East Turkestan, the the Hui
Rebellion, the
the Dungan Rebellion, etc. But the
Chinese were able to put those down.
These were Islamic rebellions against
China.
And because
the Chinese were able to put those down
and and and hold on to the territories,
that those territories eventually became
part of China. After the Communists won
in 1949, 1950, they were able to grab
these territories and hold on to them.
At that time, there was no resistance to
these things from the great powers like
the USSR or the US or anybody else
because they were
they were interested in the other things
at the time. They were preoccupied with
with other things.
And the US never has had a presence all
this way deep into Eurasia. The USSR
certainly does. So after the end of the
Second World War, 1945, the Soviets
actually could have taken Manchuria, but
they allowed the Chinese to take
Manchuria.
Because uh see, Manchuria was under
Japanese occupation from the 1930s,
mid-30s or early 30s onwards. Manchukuo
was this puppet state the Japanese had
established in uh Manchuria. And then
the Soviets were able to defeat that and
they were able to
um
you know, take possession of various
parts of Manchuria and they could have
taken the whole of Manchuria if they
wanted, but they gave it as a brotherly
gesture to the Chinese Communist Party.
Uh so that's how the Chinese got
Manchuria. That's how they got Southern
Mongolia.
Uh they got East Turkestan also. They
were able to get these territories
because they were able to send their
armies, their troops over there and hold
those territories. Making claims on a
map makes no difference in the world.
And similarly, when it comes to Tibet,
they were able to send troops and occupy
Tibet physically with the help of
Jawaharlal Nehru ji.
Yeah?
So that's how the Chinese got it and
nobody else
resisted. We did not resist when they
took Tibet.
We helped the Chinese.
Strange.
Bhaskar Pandit says, "What's the
present-day barrier humans face from
reaching Mars in person? Is it limited
to space radiation? Can't a combo of
rare earths help contain?"
Um I'm not sure how do rare earths help
contain space radiation.
Uh rare earths and space radiation
radiation, there's no connection.
Uh
If you See, radiation is
it's either the solar wind, it's cosmic
rays, it is um
gamma rays, etc. All this uh these
harmful particles and photons
that uh can damage DNA, cause cancer, do
all kinds of nasty things to human
biology. That's radiation.
Right?
So
rare earths have nothing to do with
radiation. If you want to stop radiation
from entering a spacecraft, you've got
to shield it.
See, if there's a Let's say there is uh
a gamma ray source in this room, in the
room that I am. Then in order for me to
be protected from that, shielded from
that, I will need uh something thick a
thick metal
thick substance that will be able to
stop the gamma rays. So ideally, it's
lead, lead shielding.
Uh but obviously, in space when you're
traveling across space, you don't really
come across very energetic gamma rays.
You come across other kinds of radiation
like uh the solar wind, um and and uh
cosmic rays including ultra-high energy
cosmic rays, UHECRs, etc. So you need
your spacecraft to be suitably shielded
and you don't need lead for that.
Um I mean
So when when we are when you have space
when you have astronauts in lower orbit,
let's say on the International Space
Station. Or when you have astronauts who
go to the moon
uh they do encounter radiation.
Sometimes you will have a an astronaut
whose eyes are closed closed and a
cosmic ray photon or cosmic ray particle
is going to hit the retina and with
their eyes closed, they will see a
flash.
That sort of thing happens. Right?
So there's going to be this need to have
adequate shielding for human beings or
when we send them to Mars or any other
uh part of the solar system that's
beyond the Earth orbit because over
here, we have a very strong magnetic
field, a reasonably strong magnetic
magnetic field that deflects all these
dangerous particles away from the
surface of the Earth. But if we go into
space, that's not the case. So that's
one of the barriers that we will would
be careful about, you know?
Humans should not By the time they reach
Mars in like 8, 9, 10 months, they
should not
have cancer because of exposure to
radiation, various kinds of radiation.
That's one thing.
Uh
what's the other barrier? Nothing
really.
Nothing really.
We have rockets
of various kinds. All we need to do is
to have a space capsule in which you can
keep a human being
or multiple human beings safely
and provide them with enough food, water
and uh
oxygen to make the journey to Mars and
hopefully come back.
Some people have even even doubted that
uh we can make we can have people go on
one-way journeys to Mars for whatever
reason.
I ideally want people to go and return.
And if you go to Mars and if you if you
land there, you should be able to spend
some time there and return safely. So
it's pretty complicated.
The time window is once in 28, 29 months
or whatever it is, okay? When the
planets align in the right way.
And then it takes about roughly 8, 9
months, maybe 10 months
to reach Mars if you are in that time
window
based on the alignments of the planets.
So you need to have a spacecraft that's
powerful enough to send humans there to
send a spacecraft there. The spacecraft
should be able to make a soft landing on
Mars, which is pretty difficult because
Mars is a different kind of planet. It
doesn't have the kind of atmosphere we
have here. It's got a much thinner
atmosphere.
So you're going to be able to land there
softly in a controlled manner
then you should be able to spend some
time there, maybe 3 days, maybe 1 week,
whatever it is, maybe 3 months, whatever
you want.
Then you should be able to take off from
Mars once again
and escape the gravitational pull of
Mars and then return to Earth. So it's
pretty complex.
And the technology more or less exists
today. But is it reliable? Is it Is it
foolproof? Is it Is it fail-proof?
If we send if we attempt 100 launches,
how many will succeed?
Even if it's 90% success rate, it's not
good enough, right? We want 99.9%
success rate. Only then we'll be we'll
be be willing to risk human beings
going to Mars or going
going for such missions.
But I'll tell you what.
When people would when various
militaries were developing aircraft
carriers,
okay?
When you had
aircraft taking off from ships and
landing on ships, the mortality rates
initially were very high.
And that was tolerable at the time
because that was the only way to make
progress. So, uh maybe hundreds, maybe
thousands of pilots died in these
botched landings, etc. on aircraft
carriers until
the entire thing was perfected. So,
initially there's going to be
casualties.
And uh if humanity doesn't have the the
the
the guts to take that, then probably we
will not become a spacefaring uh
civilization.
So, these are the various uh barriers
that humans face, that we face reaching
Mars. And what's the other barrier? It's
very expensive. Really, really
expensive. Unless you have have got
Unless you have massive rocket like what
Elon Musk is developing, Starship,
SpaceX, right?
Uh the kind of rocket that can launch
maybe 100 people at a time to Mars. So,
if you have that sort of economy of
scale, then it becomes cheaper. And
especially when you have reusable rocket
booster technology, etc.
So, yeah, Elon Musk is solving the big
problems and that will most likely mean
that the US will lead
the world in the space race and in the
race to reach Mars.
Bhaskar Manet says, "Can climate change
actually help Russian economy given the
last given the vast landmass for
agriculture
and permafrost defreezing that might
have minerals underneath?"
Uh okay, could global warming help the
Russian economy
given the last
the vast landmass for agriculture? Yeah,
if you got if you
if more of your land thaws
and becomes available for agriculture,
it can certainly help your economy.
Uh see, first of all, Russia is
completely self-sufficient in terms of
agriculture, right?
And it has an agricultural surplus which
it most likely exports to various
nations. I have not looked into the into
the details. So, if it's able to
you know, free up more land which
becomes agriculturally viable,
then I suppose it could export more
uh agricultural produce to various
nations which could obviously help its
economy. Uh once again, if you have
permafrost
defreezing, thawing, and you are able to
access more minerals that way, well,
yeah, it can certainly help your
economy. But see, climate change is a
slow process. Uh we're expecting maybe 2
3 degrees of of change,
uh increase, a couple of degrees of
increase this century.
How much will it free up?
And even if you you see, you can
prospect for minerals even on frozen
land where you have permafrost that
never thaws. And if you discover that
there are minerals there, you can drill
through the permafrost, too. So, when it
comes to minerals, it's not going to be
an issue. The Russians know how to drill
in totally frozen land.
Uh so, when it comes to minerals,
whether it's frozen or it's not frozen,
if the Russians find minerals, oil,
whatever there, they're going to exploit
that. That's not going to prevent the
the the land being frozen is not going
to prevent the Russians from doing
something. It's only for agriculture
that, you know, it could free up some
more land. But how much more land will
it free up? I'm not sure if it's going
to be very substantial.
And of course, there's there's going to
be some dangers of permafrost thaw
thawing because see, when you have uh
when you have
ground that's been frozen for 10,000
years and now it thaws, it's going to
throw up ancient
uh microorganisms and God knows what
else, viruses, bacteria. So, that could
actually have pretty dangerous effect on
on
on the environment and on humans more
specifically.
So, yeah, the the climate change maybe
in 50 years, 100 years, it will have the
effect of of freeing up much more
territory for uh significantly more
territory for agriculture. But when it
comes to minerals, doesn't really
matter.
Bhaskar Manet says, "Is Gandhara called
the graveyard of civilizations due to
geography and in popular popular
folklore sort of cursed landmass which
will always face warfare or turmoil?"
Well, I don't know about folklore. It is
said that uh
what? Gandhara was kind of Was it
cursed?
In the Mahabharata times?
Did Did Gandhari curse her brother
Shakuni because he got her sons involved
in all kinds of nasty stuff? Was it like
that? I'm not sure. See, I don't know
about the myth of the the folklore part.
I'm not I'm not saying Mahabharata is
mythology. Mahabharata is is history.
But uh whether he was cursed, whether
the land was cursed, I'm not really sure
about those
uh
those aspects.
Why is Gandhara called the graveyard of
civilizations? See, we don't call
Gandhara the graveyard of civilizations.
We call Afghanistan the graveyard of
civilizations.
And it's not called the graveyard of
civilizations. It's called the graveyard
of empi- empires, okay? So, which
empires are we referring to? Well, some
people like to backdate all the way to
Alexander's time. Did Alexander really
pass through Gandhara? Uh he passed
through Persia.
Did he go all the way north into
Gandhara? Maybe to some extent he may
have gone into what is now called
Afghanistan to some extent. He married
this uh
this
this lady called
Roxana, right? Roxana.
Was she from Gandhara? Was she Persian?
Probably Gandhara.
Um so, he did conquer some parts of
Gandhara, it looks like. But uh did the
people of Gandhara throw him out? Did
they defeat him in
make him withdraw? Not quite. It was his
defeat in India that made him withdraw.
So, you can't say that Afghanistan is
the was the graveyard of the Macedonian
empire. It wasn't of Alexander's empire,
it wasn't.
Uh so, which empires has Gandhara been
the graveyard of? Well, Genghis Khan
passed through Gandhara on his way to
destroying Khwarazm,
teaching the Khwarazmians Khwarazmians a
lesson.
Uh Genghis Khan passed through Gandhara
without any issue.
He returned also through Gandhara.
He did a diversion south all the way to
the west bank of the Indus chasing
Jalal-ud-din the coward and then went
back northwards through Gandhara and
then eastwards back into a reconquest of
China.
So,
Gandhara did not become the graveyard of
the
Mongol empire, not at all.
Which empire
so,
[Music]
so, Gandhara became the graveyard of
what? The British empire. The British
fought the Afghans and did not do well.
So, yeah, there is there is that. And
when it comes to
another aspect of aspect of Gandhara's
history, the Turks conquered Gandhara
and they did they turned it into
Afghanistan.
So,
Gandhara was conquered
and culturally destroyed.
So, it's not really that much of a
graveyard of empires, is it?
So, the British fared poorly
against the Afghans. Yes, no no question
about that. The Soviets tried to invade
Afghanistan, they failed.
Not because of the resilience of the To
some extent because of the resilience of
the Afghans, but actually because of the
arms, ammunition, training, etc. given
by the Americans by Pakistan.
So, you know,
and recently the Americans occupied
Afghanistan for 20 years and they left
of their own volition, right? They were
not defeated.
So, you can make any kind of mythology
up about a region,
but the truth is that Gandhara was
Indian and there it was smashed, its
culture was destroyed, and it was turned
into Afghanistan.
Its ethnicity was diluted. All kinds of
Turkic people came and settled in in
Gandhara.
So, you know, the history is actually
quite tragic, actually.
Bhaskar Manet says, "Humans are
incredibly inherently violent with
animal-like instincts." Well, we are
technically animals, aren't we? We
belong to the family of animals. So,
we're going to have those instincts. The
instincts that chimpanzees have, we
share those instincts. Instincts that
gorillas and bonobos and orangutans have
and gibbons have,
we share those instincts, no question
about that. The instincts that wolves
and cats have, those instincts also we
share.
And so much more. So, look, we are
we are human beings. We are a different
species, but we are part of the animal
family, okay? So, humans are inherently
violent with animal-like instincts, of
of course.
Then by definition, achieving Kardashev
type one
um scale impossible for humanity later
on, two or three.
Why? Why is it impossible?
Why is it impossible?
Just because we have certain instincts
doesn't make it impossible.
No.
Absolutely not.
For humanity to achieve Kardashev type
one civilization status, what will it
mean first of all? What is the Kardashev
scale? So, if you look at my YouTube
channel and you look and you search for
Kardashev in the search box, you will
find multiple video clips of me
answering the same question over and
over. What is the Kardashev scale and
all that. Where do we stand on the
scale, etc.
The Kardashev scale, if you are a type
one civilization, it means that you are
able to harness the entire energy output
of your
local of your home planet.
All the energy output of your home
planet, you're able to harness and
control it. So, we obviously aren't able
to harness and control the energy output
of our planet. We can't There's so much
wind energy that completely is wasted,
right? Essentially, you can call it
waste because we don't harness it.
There's so much wave energy, waves,
ocean waves, etc. That energy we don't
we don't harness it at all.
Uh
most of the rivers, we don't tap the
hydro hydroelectric
potential of those rivers. We aren't
able to
you know, tap into the energy of
tectonic activity of earthquakes, etc.
Um so much more.
So, we are definitely not a type one
civilization. Maybe some people say that
we are 0.7 or something. I'm not sure
about even 0.7.
I would say that, you know,
if you can't tap even 10% of the wind
energy
and wave energy, then you are not even
0.3.
So, we are way below you know, type one
status.
But,
humanity can achieve type one status.
It's certainly possible. There's nothing
There is nothing in the laws of physics
that prevents is is that is
capable of preventing us from achieving
type one status. What will need we need
to do to achieve that?
First of all, we will have to stop
fighting among each other.
So, that's where
Bhaskar Bandit's point comes in that we
are inherently violent inherently
violent. We
It's not about animal-like instincts
that is the problem. Those instincts are
fine. We have tribalistic instincts.
We grew We band into small groups. Now
it's called nations in the past it was
called something else, empires,
kingdoms. In the future you may have
something else, clans, tribes, whatever.
And we fight each other. All of our
energy is spent doing all these things.
Within India,
most of the energy, economic energy,
other energy of India is spent fighting
each other,
arguing all the time, fighting in three
million elections every 10 years and God
knows what. So, all of our energy is
dissipated within.
So, what will it take for humanity to
break free of all of this and achieve
type one status? We're going to have
need a one world government for that to
happen, which is actually a very scary
prospect. But yeah, it certainly can
happen.
It certainly can happen.
So, I don't think it's impossible. I
think it is uh
I think it's very hard to achieve, but
it's definitely not impossible. Why do I
say it's not impossible impossible? I
say this because there is nothing in the
laws of physics
that makes it impossible. It's just if
we if we can surpass and transcend
certain issues that we have with with
ourselves, we can do it.
But, like I say, it's easier said than
done.
Bhaskar Bandit says, "Best way to spend
weekends is watching you. Thank you,
sir."
Uh
"Lots of love and support. We'll never
stop raising our standards. Looking
forward to soft copies of your book in
the future. Thank you so much, sir.
Thank you so much. I really appreciate
it."
I really appreciate uh your support,
your viewership, all of you. So, thank
you very much. And to you, sir, Bhaskar
Bandit. Thank you.
Ganapathy says, "Was the attack by the
Afghan migrant in Washington a false
flag attack?
Trump is using that as an excuse to end
all third world immigration."
Well,
look, I don't know.
Is it
Is it possible? It's possible, but was
it a false flag attack? I am not in a
position to know that. Right?
It's possible that it may have been a
false flag attack. Why is it possible
now?
So, this Afghan gentleman
who carried out this uh
this Afghan migrant, not gentleman. He
he
So, he carried out this attack, right?
What was his background like? He was
trained by the Americans. He was He was
an Afghan national. He was trained by
the Americans. He had links to the ISI.
So, that raises very big very loud red
flags clearly, right?
So, so he's been trained by the
Americans. He has links to Pakistan. He
has links to the ISI. And he has been
brought into the US.
He's been given residence in the US for
whatever reason. And then he goes ahead
and does this terror attack.
So, if he was controlled by let's say US
intelligence services in the past, what
is
is there anything to prevent him him
still from still being controlled in
some way by US intelligence agencies?
Nothing, right? So, it's possible that
somebody within the US intelligence,
potentially, possibly, hypothetically,
could have used him as a pawn to create
this situation, which would give Trump
the excuse to end third world migration,
whatever. It is possible.
But do we have evidence? We don't have
evidence. So, I can't say yes or no. I
can only say it's possible.
Tanmay Deshpande says,
"A big fan. Thank you. Santaji and
Santaji and Dhanaji were ruthless
Maratha warriors
crucial
to the 27-year war against the Mughals.
They are not known and deserve
spotlight. Can you Google it if possible
for others as well?"
Okay, let's Google it because I haven't
studied Maratha history in any
significant detail, so I
myself won't be able to tell you, but
let's see.
Santaji
Dhanaji
Santaji Dhanaji
Santaji and Dhanaji were two of the most
important Maratha generals who fought
against the Mughal Empire in the late
17th century. Santaji Ghorpade
was known for his strict discipline and
fearsome military tactics, while Dhanaji
Jadhav was more lenient with his troops,
but equally effective, particularly in
in campaigns against Mughal incursions
into Maharashtra and Karnataka.
Together they are credited with helping
the Maratha Empire survive after the
death of Sambhaji Maharaj and preventing
its defeat by the Mughals. Santaji
Ghorpade, military style, strict
disciplinarian, known for his harshness,
but also his strategic brilliance.
Key achievements, attacked Mughal
general Sheikh Nizam and captured his
army in 1689. Led daring raids and was
known to have inflicted significant
defeats on many top Mughal generals.
His reputation was so fearsome that
Mughal records noted facing him often
often meant defeat or capture.
Challenges, his strict nature sometimes
caused friction with other Maratha
leaders even and even with his own
within his own regiment. Dhanaji Jadhav,
military style, had a more lax approach
to his troops, which made him popular
with them, but he was still a successful
commander. Key achievements, fought
again alongside
Santaji in major campaigns including the
defeat of Sheikh Nizam in 1689
and preventing Mughal advances into
Karnataka. Served as the Maratha
Senapati, commander-in-chief, and played
a pivotal role in expanding Maratha
influence in Gujarat. His tactical
maneuvering was kept crucial in halting
Mughal incursions into Maratha
territory. Combined impact, together
Santaji and Dhanaji led successful
campaigns that kept the Maratha Empire
from collapsing during a crucial period.
Their combined strength and tactical
prowess were also influ- were
instrumental in the Maratha resistance
against the Mughals. They are considered
two of the most of the foremost Maratha
then generals before the Peshwa era. All
right, very interesting, very very
important generals both of them. And
clearly they were their their
uh
their efforts were crucial to the
Maratha Empire
uh
to the Marathas
resisting
uh
the Mughal
invaders, occupiers of India.
Outstanding.
Okay, UMX
G etc. says, "How did the Scandinavians
become so rich historically poor?"
I think you asked me this question
yesterday also, right?
How did Scandinavia become so rich? Is
it really very rich? I think it's
Today it is reasonably rich.
Okay, you
um
See, overall, Europe was never dirt
poor. Okay? Uh there were times maybe a
thousand years ago
when the overall
GDP of Europe was much lower than what
it is today, GDP per capita, let's say.
But Scandinavia was was home to the
Vikings, wasn't it? Scandinavia is where
the Vikings emerged from, and they were
very successful, very fearsome warriors,
and they ruled various parts of Western
Europe for
at least a couple of centuries. They did
incessant raids into the UK, what is
today the UK. They took a lot of plunder
from there. So, they became pretty rich,
actually. Then they were converted to
Christianity,
and they became a Christian region, but
they were never dirt poor or
historically poor as such, right?
Um
And overall, that's that's the thing.
Now, how did this happen? Look, I
haven't studied their history in great
detail, so I won't be able to tell you.
Uh
You asked I think you it was you who
asked me the same question yesterday
also.
Um I don't know the specifics. I haven't
looked into the history of the
Scandinavian nations.
But uh
what
What are their sources of of income,
trade, etc.? What do they export?
I It's either fisheries, it's either oil
and gas, it's something or the other.
I can't tell you in detail right now.
Okay, James James says,
"Uh would it Would you
Would you like it better if the French
colonized you?
Maybe they offered you a sweeter
language, and you would eat the
croissant for breakfast."
Well, peut-être the French would have
been better than the accursed uh
uh the beef the beefsteak. No, the roast
beef. Le roast beef.
So, the British like to call the French
the frogs for whatever reason. And the
French like to call the British le roast
beef.
Because the Bri- British like to eat
roast beef. So, le roast beef.
And the British and the French have this
historical 1,000-year animosity towards
each other.
Um dates back to the year at least the
year 1066 AD when this guy what's his
name Guillaume Guillaume le bâtard.
William the bastard.
He ended up conquering England, right?
And from then onwards he was known as
William the Conqueror.
And the British and the the English and
the French have hated each other for a
thousand years and they've fought each
other so many times. Battle of Agincourt
and so much more. The Hundred Year War.
The British burned that girl alive. She
was 16. What? Joan of Arc. Joan of Arc,
right? And so on. See, at the end of the
day I'll tell you what. It would not
have mattered who colonized us.
I would like it better if none of you
barbarians had colonized us.
Right? Cuz the French they they were
they were no better than the English.
Uh you had this guy called Dupleix,
right? Dupleix, g u p l e i x who was
the governor general of whatever part of
some parts of southern India.
Um and and he destroyed temples and
built churches on top of them.
So the French were no better than the
British. If the French colonized us we
would be speaking in in French today,
yes? What difference does it make? One
foreign language another foreign
language.
And we would perhaps eat croissant for
breakfast, but what
what difference does it make? So I would
I would like it better if nobody had
colonized us, but that's all wishful
thinking.
What's happened has happened.
And we Indians need to go need to
decolonize which we aren't doing right
now.
For a variety of reasons.
So the answer is no, it makes no
difference. Whether it's the British if
if it's the French
Portuguese the Portuguese
would have made no difference. It would
have been the same thing.
Uh Ganapathy says, "What has happened to
Imran Khan alive or dead?" You see I can
answer this question only if I have
recently been to Pakistan to whatever
place he is being held, right? I can
only answer the question if I have been
there. Now there are all these Indian
YouTubers who are geopolitical analysts
and experts who are giving all kinds of
fantastic insights into what's happened
to Imran Khan. How do they know what's
happened?
Oh, I have sources in Pakistan.
Good for you, sir. I have no sources in
Pakistan. I am not in connection with
any Pakistani.
So what's happened to Imran Khan alive
or dead? I can tell you we don't know
what's happened to him.
There's been a long period of time since
no one has heard from him. Apparently
his sisters are not being allowed to
visit him.
He has a couple of sisters, I believe.
Uh probably older than him.
And they obviously will want to be able
to visit him from time to time because
their brother their family members in is
in is
um confined illegally in prison.
But at least I don't know 30 40 days
they've not been allowed to see him.
So there's been a silence about Imran
Khan. So it looks like something may
have happened. That's why there are all
these speculations that are swirling on
social media and mainstream media as
well.
But what's happened I don't know. Looks
like something may have happened. Maybe
they may have killed him off, but we
don't have evidence thus far.
Critical thinker says, "Right wing, left
wing, far right, far left in politics."
What what's the question?
Are you saying where do I stand?
Are you saying where should everybody
stand?
What are you asking me?
Where do I stand if you may if you're
asking me?
I am definitely right of center.
I'm not a centrist.
You got to take a stand somewhere in
life, right? So I'm not a centrist. I'm
definitely not a lefty. I'll be
somewhere on the right.
Far right, moderate right, I don't know.
You guys decide.
I'm definitely somewhere on the right.
Uh Dark Knight says, "The US flag is
nearly identical to the East India
Company flag. The deep state is
basically the inheritors of the East
India Company's loot, isn't it? They are
likely the ones
They likely are the ones who own the
Federal Reserve, too."
The US flag and the East India Company
flag. Let's take a look.
Uh US flag.
Okay, let's just look for the East India
Company flag.
East India Company
Company flag. What's it look like? Ooh.
Well, well, well, well, well, well,
well.
Very interesting, yes, isn't it? Very
interesting.
The flag of the East India Company.
So you replace the Union Jack with the
50 with the 50 stars and there you have
the US flag. Which is very interesting,
right? It's pretty similar. It's clearly
the same pattern.
Now that is the deep state
the inheritors of the East India
Company's loot?
What I what we can say what we can say
for sure is this. The US is a
continuation of the British Empire.
The US has carried the mantle forward
the flag forward the torch forward.
In 1944-45 all that happened was that
the center of power
shifted westwards from London, UK to
Washington, D.C.
District Columbia. That's all. But the
same entity has continued.
So
the British Empire still exists. It's
been augmented vastly and it's now
called the US Empire.
It's called the rules-based world order
or whatever the latest thing the
Americans call call the thing.
So the United States is the inheritor.
It's the continuation of the British
Empire. Now when it comes to the British
Empire there's a small number of people
who controlled it.
I suppose they still control who
whatever happens in the US Empire,
right?
Or they or their descendants control it.
They're they're inheritors the ones who
took forward the legacy.
Um
So it's not about the loot.
It's not about the loot. Please
understand.
It's not about the loot.
All the money they looted plundered from
India
it was
it's not sitting somewhere in some dark
room.
It was used to create things.
Money is fuel.
Gold is fuel.
You spend it to create things to
purchase things.
The British used all that money to
create this
gigantic global empire, right?
To create an empire that spans the world
you have to set up ports. You have to
set up you have to build hundreds maybe
thousands of ships. You have to you have
to uh
conscript hundreds of thousands of
soldiers. You have to buy allegiances in
58 different countries. You have to pay
off the local warlords.
That's how you build an empire.
To do that you have to burn something.
You have to burn fuel which is money.
But by doing that you acquire
more power. You acquire more resources.
So by spending let's say x amount of
gold you may get three times that five
times that.
So that's what the British did.
All that money they stole from India
plundered from India is not sitting in
some dark room somewhere.
It's all been spread across the world to
create the British Empire which
eventually became the US Empire and the
US has augmented it vastly.
And yeah, so that's the deal. That's the
deal about the deep state. A small
number of men like Chamath Palihapitiya
would say it's about 150 men only men
who control what happens in the entire
world.
And they don't want themselves to be
known. And they most likely own the
Federal Reserve. Yes.
Ganapathy says, "When and how why did
the Brahmins become vegetarian?" Okay,
when and why did the Brahmins become
vegetarian?
If you study the Rigveda
nobody is vegetarian. All the Rigveda
says is that you may not eat beef.
You cannot kill cows. It doesn't talk
about eating cows. It says you cannot
kill cows.
Anyone who kills cows will be given the
harshest of punishments.
So in the Rigveda it says you can't kill
humans unless they are nasty people or
whatever.
Otherwise you can't kill humans and you
can't kill cows and you can't kill
horses unless you are a Chakravarti
Samrat who's doing the Ashwamedha Yagna.
In that case case you may kill you may
sacrifice the horse Ashwamedha Yagna.
So in the Rigveda nobody is vegetarian.
That is very clear and you can't
challenge that.
Go to the original source and read it.
And then try to challenge what I'm
saying. You can't. So no one was
vegetarian during the Rigvedic time.
Then during the
Atharvaveda Yajur etc. you will have
lists of animals that can't be killed.
But even then other animals could be
eaten. So what happened?
How did large portions of India become
vegetarian?
What happened?
See the the advent of Buddhism.
Buddhism was this obscure fringe
religious path
that had emerged sometime maybe 2500
years ago.
And it was going nowhere, but this guy
our great emperor Ashoka for political
reasons decided to bring Buddhism
mainstream.
And he propagated Buddhism far and wide
not just within the subcontinent, but
beyond.
So overnight within a few decades during
Ashoka's time and afterwards Buddhism
became a global like a global phenomenon
because of the street patronage imperial
patronage given by Ashoka.
Otherwise Buddhism would
probably have gone the same way as the
Ajivikas.
But Ashoka decided to suppress the
Ajivikas and and promote Buddhism. So
Buddhism becomes a big deal and the
Buddhists go after all other
all other paths of Hindu Dharma of of of
Dharma. Everything is inferior. We are
the best.
Our path is the best. You Brahmins you
do Yagnas. You do these Yagnas and you
sacrifice animals. You are evil.
Buddhism is all about compassion blah
blah blah.
And that's why Buddhism became prevalent
across India.
All across India.
So, because of that
Brahmins who were now being accused of
being animal killers,
they had to make a tactical decision.
The tactical decision was, we will
become even more extreme than you
Buddhists. You Buddhists still eat
animals sometimes.
We're going to go full veg.
And that's how they became vegetarian.
And that's how all these
vegetarian doctrines come into the play
and become
more prevalent.
And then now you have plenty of Hindus
who don't eat meat at all. So, it's it's
a matter of choice. I'm not saying it's
a good thing or a bad thing. It's
entirely your choice, but this is how it
happened.
It's because of the pressure applied by
the the
Buddhists
that Brahmins had to make this tactical
choice to become completely vegetarian.
V S V S says, "What's your opinion on
the rule of Gaddafi? Was it barbaric or
actually good for his people? Why didn't
America take advantage of Libya after
2011?"
What do you mean by take advantage of
Libya?
I mean, what do you want the Americans
to do to Libya?
How do you take advantage of Libya?
What you want to do
is if you have a guy who's ruling this
country and he's opposed to you, you get
rid of him.
Then you install some kind of third-rate
puppet government, it doesn't matter.
And ensure that whatever oil gas exists
oil gas or resources exist in Libya,
those flow into your lap. That's all you
do.
And did the Americans not ensure this
happens? Of course, they ensured this
happens. So, if you mean that as taking
advantage of Libya, they did that. Now,
what's my opinion on the rule of
Gaddafi?
Gaddafi was a good ruler for his people.
Of course, he would have oppressed some
people in his country.
Show me a country where there's no
oppression. Look at the United States of
America. Have you read the history of
the United States of America?
You think they are less they have been
less oppressive than Libya?
Please do some actual studying if you
think that the US is a super benevolent
country and they are far better than the
Libya or Iraq during Saddam Hussein.
Do you have any idea of the of the
ethnic cleansing that's happened in the
US? Of the genocide that's happened in
the US? Of the slavery of people that's
happened in the US? Of the racial
segregation that's happened in the US?
You have no idea.
Right?
So, let's let's not
So, now when it comes to Gaddafi,
obviously he would have oppressed some
people.
Anyone who stands against him, he would
have
dealt with them in the in the
appropriate fashion, let's say. He would
have done that for sure. But how was
life
during Gaddafi's rule in Libya? If you
were an ordinary citizen of Libya who
did not go and shout against Gaddafi,
life would have been stable. Life would
have been reasonably prosperous for you.
Your education, your children's
education was taken care of.
I believe health care was free.
Education was free.
There was law and order. There was very
little crime.
Yeah, of course, you were not allowed to
question Gaddafi or protest against him.
If you did that, well,
don't say we didn't warn you.
But as long as you behaved the same way
you behave in China, you don't shout
against Xi Jinping, as long as you did
those things, life was good.
Right?
So, I don't
Gaddafi was he barbaric? Absolutely not.
He was good for his people, those who
stood with him and most people stood
with him.
Why would they not?
But problem is that just like Cuba,
he opposed the US.
How did he oppose the US? He wanted to
set up an African currency backed by
gold. That's number one. And number two,
he chose to sell oil
the to whoever he wanted and not go by
American dictats.
That made him very nasty, very very bad,
very naughty boy.
And that's why he had to be taken care
of, and he was. That's what happens.
And there was this
there was this meeting of the
Organization of Islamic Countries, OIC.
Okay?
And you had all these
various Arab leaders who were sitting
there and Gaddafi is giving a speech
and he's saying, "The Americans are
coming after me, but do do you what do
you people think? They is not they
they're not going to come after you
someday?"
And you had Bashar al-Assad sitting in
sitting there and smiling.
Kind of laughing at at Gaddafi.
Well, where is Bashar al-Assad today?
Where is he today?
Gaddafi was right.
Right. Critical Thinker says, "When
black hole evaporates, what happens to
the information that fell into it? Does
quantum information get destroyed?
Please explain how black black holes
die."
Okay.
What do you mean by black holes
evaporate first of all, right? This term
is used by physicists, black hole
evaporation.
What is black hole made of water? Are
black holes made of water? Do they
evaporate? What's the deal?
See, there's a phenomenon called Hawking
radiation.
We see, most people think of black holes
as these giant cosmic vacuum cleaners
that suck everything inside, right? If
there's a black hole passing near you,
it's going to suck you in. That's what
you imagine. But that's not quite the
case. Black holes are simply
pure mass, essentially.
Pure mass with perhaps Yeah, they they
can have charge and angular momentum,
but that's all it is. So, a black hole
has only three properties that you can
see from the outside.
It has mass, it has charge, it has
angular momentum. It may or may not have
charge, but most
you know, observable black holes will
have some charge because of absorbed
stuff, right? Which will have charge.
So, that's what a black hole is and it
doesn't necessarily try and suck
everything in.
Now, Stephen Hawking
in the 1960s, I believe, he discovered
through purely mathematical
calculations, semi-classical
calculations,
not purely quantum calculation, but
semi-classical calculations,
he discovered
that black holes actually have a
temperature.
Black holes have a temperature.
They have entropy. The entropy is
proportional to the surface area.
Entropy is the measure of disorder of
any system.
So, black holes have entropy.
The entropy part came from Bekenstein, I
think. Uh but Hawking discovered that
black holes have temperature. Now, if
something has temperature, it radiates.
Any object that has a temperature
radiates something or the other.
It either radiates infrared
waves, infrared
radiation, which is just photons,
or it radiates particles.
So, Hawking was able to demonstrate
mathematically that black holes radiate
and he was able to
to calculate the rate at which a black
hole will radiate based on its mass. So,
from the from the mass of a black hole
and its
If you know the mass, you know its
radius, 2mg by c squared. 2mg by c
squared, g is the large g that's
Newton's
gravitational constant, m is the mass, c
is the speed of light. So, the
Schwarzschild radius of a black hole is
2mg by c squared.
Now, if you know the mass, you know the
radius.
If you know the mass and the radius,
you're going to know the the temperature
of the black hole.
Temperature in degrees Kelvin, not
degrees Kelvin, in Kelvin.
The temperature in Kelvin, which is you
can convert that to Celsius.
And based on that, you can calculate the
rate at which the black hole is
radiating mass energy, mass \
energy.
So, it's the rate at which the black
hole is losing mass and that's what we
call Hawking radiation, which is also
called called black hole evaporation.
Now, when a black hole evaporates, loses
mass, what does it radiate? It radiates
whatever.
And and the thing about Hawking
radiation and temperature is that the
larger a black hole is, the colder it
gets.
And the smaller a black hole is, the
hotter it gets.
So, if you are if a black hole becomes
smaller, it gets hotter, which means it
means it radiates more, which makes it
smaller even faster, which makes it
makes it even hotter, which makes it
smaller even faster. So, the end stage
of a black hole's life is an explosive
explosion. Explosive explosion, very
funny. Okay. It's an explosion. So,
black holes die with a bang if they do
die eventually, right?
So, that's the deal about Hawking
radiation.
Um
What is this radiation like? It's pure
blackbody radiation.
Okay, it's it's a it's got a pure
blackbody spectrum, completely random.
And it can be photons, it can be
neutrinos, it can be
um
protons, antiprotons, whatever. All
kinds of particles just
are spewed out by the black hole. If
it's a very cold black hole, it's going
to radiate either photons or or even
gravitons if gravitons exist.
So, now when we now that we understood
what is black hole radiation, etc., what
happens to the information that fell
into it? We don't quite know. See,
information let's What's information?
Let's say a photon is absorbed by the
black hole. The photon contains
information. It contains polarization of
the It contains polarization
information. Photons have polarization.
So, what happened to that information?
We don't know. Once you cross the event
horizon, we don't know
we don't quite know what happens inside.
Right?
And we don't even know if there's a real
singularity at the heart of the black
hole.
Um, it is said that the information
paradox has been resolved these days.
I'm not quite sure about that, but uh
does this quantum information get get
destroyed? Does it get scrambled? See,
eventually if everything
Eventually information all comes out,
but it may come out in a different shape
and form.
Uh so, does it get destroyed entirely?
The the polarization of a photon
will we be able to recover that? Or does
it get scrambled? Do we need some kind
of algorithm to unscramble it? Um
I think
we are not quite sure yet about what
happens to the quantum information.
Uh is information destroyed? I don't
think information is destroyed, but it
does get scrambled or jumbled and
converted into some other shape or form
of information, but everything does come
out eventually.
So, that overall is the deal. And
I hope that explains how black holes
die. Black holes can die, but there are
some black holes like super massive
black holes at the center of galaxies
that are so large that their lifetime
is
longer than the current age of the
universe, which is paradoxical, but it
means that they will live a very very
long time.
Game Changer says, "Why is India
backward in innovation and invention
than Western countries? When will the
system How will the system be improved?"
Why is India backward in innovation and
invention?
First, number one positive factor. The
third-rate rotten education system of
India.
Okay?
The Indian education system is rotten to
the core.
It emphasizes when you are a student, it
emphasizes learning three languages. So,
let's say you have like five, six How
many subjects do you have in high school
in a year? Let's say you have seven
subjects that you have to study or eight
subjects. Out of this, three are going
to be
languages. You're going to have to study
Hindi, you're going to have to study the
local language, and you have to study
English if you want to have a decent
chance in life. So, out of those eight
subjects, three are languages. You're
wasting your time learning three
languages. Second, all the other stuff
you have to memorize, memorize,
memorize. All you are learning in the
Indian education system is how to pass
exams. You're not actually learning any
new knowledge.
The moment your exam is done, you're
going to clear your mind. And you're
going to forget everything. That's how
That's what happens to everybody.
Then there is this
emphasis on the rote memorization, ratta
marna.
Rote memorization.
There's no emphasis on actually
understanding the concepts,
understanding cause and effect, nothing.
When they teach you history, memorize
dates, dates, dates, dates, dates.
Who the hell cares about your goddamn
dates? You don't understand causality.
No, there is no emphasis on critical
thinking,
on understanding what's right, what's
wrong, how to differentiate right from
wrong. None of this. And then, when it
comes to the sciences,
yeah?
When it comes to the sciences, where is
the focus on research and development?
Research.
Where is the focus on research? Even at
the university level, even at the IIT
level, what research is happening in
India?
Nothing.
You go to the See, I am not going to
take any names of any institutions, but
go to X or Y
or Z IIT.
Go to the Go to the labs.
If you go to one of the top IITs in the
country, okay, I'm not saying which one,
anyone, any of the top IITs in the
country, you go to the
You go to the um
conference room or or
that sort of thing, you will see it's
very well equipped. Latest modern
projectors and
you know, LCDs, LED screens and whatnot.
Very well equipped. You go to the
washroom. Beautiful crore rupee
washroom.
You go to the lab, the equipment is
going to be 20, 30 years old. So, that's
the kind of priorities your bureaucrats
have who are running the show.
And what's the quality of your teachers?
Most of them are mediocre.
Most of the professors, they have been
promoted through internal politicking.
So, how are you going to have
innovation, invention, et cetera?
And when it comes So, that's about the
education system, rotten to the core.
Your new education policy is not going
to solve any of the problems. It's
actually introducing more problems, it
looks like, from what I've seen, from
the little that I've seen.
That's the education system. Now, when
it comes to
industry,
what is the innovation in industry?
Where
What percentage of industry budget
is spent on R&D, research and
development? Less than 1%.
In other nations, let's say it's like 2
and 1/2, 3, 4, 5%. India, it's less than
1%.
So, first of all, you have students who
are coming out of the education system
without anything in their mind, who who
are who who have been mentally
lobotomized, who are incapable of
learning, who have no skills. Then you
put them in industry, where there is no
research and development, nothing. The
only emphasis is on to make money for
the short term.
So, when you have this system, this
self-defeating system, you're not going
to have any innovation, you're not going
to have any inventions.
Those students, those young people who
want to innovate, who want to innovate,
invent something, they have only one
choice, leave the country and go
somewhere else and work as as a
second-class citizen somewhere. Or maybe
not even a citizen, maybe a green card
holder for 20, 30 years.
That's the system. That's the That's the
deal. Well, how will the system be
improved? The system will improve when
we will have better leadership in the
country.
Shishir
Upadhyay says, "My opinion on
psychedelics."
My opinion is that they they seem to be
interesting.
Um
Experience, none. I have no experience
with psychedelics.
Um
My opinion is that they could be
interesting, but there are multiple
people,
very prominent people who who seem to
have had positive uh
experiences. Steve Jobs is an example.
He took what? LSD he took or something?
LSD is a psychedelic, isn't it?
Uh LSD or something he had taken. Um
Steve Steve Jobs, we know he's the
founder of Apple, co-founder of Apple
with Steve Wozniak. And um
he founded Apple when he was pretty
young.
And before he founded Apple, he spent
some time in India. He came to India in
search of wisdom and knowledge and all
that.
And he wanted to meet Neem Karoli Baba,
but Neem Karoli Baba had passed away.
Then he absorbed all all kinds of
various experiences and knowledge from
India. He also dabbled in Zen Buddhism.
And all all of that formed his
worldview. He became a vegetarian,
lifelong vegetarian,
et cetera. And um
as a young person, he consumed LSD
on certain occasions, and he says that
it was one of the most transformative
experiences of his life. That's what he
says.
And there are other people also who
have
uh reported similar experiences. So, it
looks like it's interesting, but I
personally have never tried have never
had the opportunity to try to try any
such thing, so I can't say.
And that's all, but um look, I am not
trying to advocate for anyone taking
such things.
Uh it's very it's very possible that
these things may have bad effects also.
So, yeah, that's what I
that's what I think about this. I don't
really know personally about it, but
sounds interesting in some ways, but
it's also potentially quite dangerous if
the um
if the
um
the thing you take it is not pure or
whatever, right? If it's tainted or
whatever, it could be very dangerous for
you. And even if it's pure, it could end
up causing some harm to you. So, I have
no idea.
Uh Swastik Mahesh says, "Why certain
castes historically barred from entering
temples before British Raj despite the
fact that caste system was British
creation?"
Listen.
There are some temples where women are
only allowed, men are not allowed.
Because of the tradition of the local
deity.
There are certain temples where women
are not allowed because let's say
Hanuman temple or or whatever. Because
of the tradition of the local deity.
Now, in India we had the varna jati
system.
The varna jati system, it evolved over
thousands of years, yeah?
It all begins See, it all begins with
the
with the defeat of the coalition of 10
plus kings to King Sudas.
So, King Sudas conquers the Indian
subcontinent. He expels all those clans
out of India.
And then, he does this yajna,
and he tells everyone, all the people of
India, that you know what? I worship
Indra, I worship all these gods, the
Vedic gods, but when I do the yajna,
your gods are also welcome.
So, this is the social contract. This is
the civilizational contract. We are the
We are all one people.
Everyone's god is welcome
to do the yajna. So, that's how our
civilization started. Now, we had this
jati varna system that that evolved over
thousands of years. You had
four major varnas. At times there were
seven varnas as as reported by
by what's his name, Megasthenes, but
eventually four varnas. That's what the
British classified it as. And you had
thousands or tens of thousands of jatis.
Now, all these gods that were welcomed
at the yajna, the sacred fire, the agni
of the yajna, these gods came from
thousands, tens of thousands of
different traditions,
folk traditions, local traditions,
village traditions, family traditions.
And each god has its own preferences.
So, you
built So, if you are in a certain
village, you will worship one specific
deity who is central to that village and
worship nowhere else.
But, you will say that this deity is an
is is an is an aspect of
Bhagwan Vishnu or whatever.
But, this deity has very specific
preferences.
And the deity must only be worshipped by
the people who consider this deity to be
whatever. So, you're going to have a
temple and you will allow only those
people to enter the temple who are from
the village or whatever.
It's similar to the Zoroastrians.
You go to a agiyari.
Agiyari is a fire temple. You have
agiyaris in India. You have agiyaris in
Gujarat. You have agiyaris in Mumbai.
You go to a fire temple
and see the sign of the door.
Non-Zoroastrians are not allowed.
So, why are other castes barred?
Because only Zoroastrians are allowed.
That is their tradition.
We may not understand their traditions.
That's why we should not go in. Do we
protest? We don't protest.
When you go to Mecca or Medina,
it says non-Muslims are not allowed. Do
we protest?
So, why are Indians so hell-bent on
on on on self-flagellation?
Why are we hell-bent on
self-flagellation? We have the most
incredibly diverse set of traditions.
Each deity has very specific
rules.
And we've got to follow those rules. If
you don't worship that deity, then why
do you want to enter the temple? Leave
those people alone. Leave the deity
alone.
Right?
And it is alleged that, you know,
certain castes are not allowed in
Brahminical temples or whatever.
That is not the case.
Every caste every every jati
has its own temples. And other jatis are
not allowed. So, Brahmins won't be
allowed in so many temples.
But, today we have to democratize
everything. All temples have to be open
to everyone. Why?
Why?
Why can't we respect our own ancient
traditions?
We don't insist on entering Zoroastrian
temples. We don't insist on going to
Mecca, Medina, or whatever.
We don't want to encroach on other
people's
red lines.
So, why do we have to encroach on each
other's red lines?
I just don't get it.
I don't get it, really.
Ganapathy says, "Did the Indian
Independent Act 1947 have certain
conditions that we had to agree to to
get independence? After all, we were
given independence under their terms.
What could those conditions be?" I have
no idea.
No idea. I think Anuj Dhar has more idea
than me.
And I've had Anuj Dhar on my podcast
like at least three times.
Um but, we have not discussed these uh
specific aspects on camera.
Um not even off camera, by the way.
Could there have been certain conditions
that we had to agree to? It's possible.
Were there some secret clauses
in the act or agreement or whatever?
It's possible. Do I know those things,
those secret things? No, I don't know
those things.
So, it is possible that there may have
been certain conditions that we may have
to agree to.
It's possible.
But, now ask yourselves this question.
Let's say, hypothetically, that there
were some secret conditions that we had
to agree to and put our signatures on in
1947. Does it mean that we have to agree
to those goddamn conditions today?
That's what Indians don't seem to get,
right?
If we signed the Indus Waters Treaty in
1960 or whatever,
does it mean we have to keep on obeying
that today?
If something is not in your interests,
are you required to keep following that?
You're not. You can walk away from a
treaty.
The Chinese had this treaty with the
British
about Hong Kong.
One nation, two systems. The Chinese
walked away unilaterally from the
treaty. They said it's it's now no
longer
in our interests to, you know, we we
will no longer
abide by this treaty. They walked away
from the treaty.
The Americans had signed this JCPOA
with Iran. Joint Comprehensive Plan of
Action.
Uh the Iran nuclear deal. Trump
unilaterally walked away from it.
So, my point is even if we signed
certain secret conditions in 1947,
we are under no obligation to abide by
those things. And that's something we
have to understand.
Hrithik Powar says, "If China makes a
move on Arunachal or Ladakh, what
leverage do we have? That's what
That's what Russia or the US want to
weaken China and India?"
If China makes a rule a move on
Arunachal or Ladakh, what leverage do we
have?
We have a military.
This This is not about leverage. This is
about a response.
Leverage is used in negotiations.
In warfare, you don't use leverage. You
use weapons.
You understand?
Leverage is not used in warfare.
Leverage is used in negotiations, in
diplomacy,
in arm-twisting,
in bullying. That's where you use
leverage.
If China makes a physical military move
on Ladakh or Arunachal, we don't use
leverage.
We use our military. We use our We use
our armed forces. We use missiles,
aircraft, tanks, whatever it takes.
That's what we do.
Okay?
Um
So,
does Russia and the US want to weaken
China and India? Russia doesn't want
that.
Russia doesn't want to weaken China and
Russia doesn't want to weaken India.
Russia will be happy with the status quo
the way it is right now.
They would actually Russia would
actually prefer for India to get
stronger vis-a-vis China.
The Americans would love to have a
weakened China and India.
But, if they if you give them a choice
of who would you like to be weaker,
China or India, they would say, "Let's
weaken India right now. It is easier
easier to do than China."
So, that's the deal. So, Russia is not
in
it doesn't want a weakened India.
It wants a stronger India vis-a-vis
China. But, the US would like India to
be significantly weaker. And China also
would like that. That's the deal.
UMX says, "PM Modi urges 10-year
national pledge to shed colonial mindset
rooted in Macaulay's legacy thoughts."
I am very fond of um decolonization.
It's not that that I'm fond of
decolonization. I'm not
fond of decolonization.
I think it is a
we have an urgent need for urgent
decolonization.
But, what do I think about what Prime
Minister has Modi has urged?
Well, it's a good thing that he has
urged this. But, the question is how?
How?
How are we going to do it?
By urging people to do it?
To shed the colonial mindset, you have
to reform the education system.
Is that being done?
So, you know,
all these slogans are nice and all these
pledges and
all these exhortations, they are
fantastic, great. But, my point is how
are you going to make this happen?
You can't tell people to decolonize
decolonize. They don't even know the
meaning of decolonize.
They don't even know that they are
colonized mentally.
They don't even understand what is the
legacy of this Macaulayan thing. What is
this Macaulayan thing? Is it the boy
from from Home Alone?
Macaulay Culkin? Or is it Lord Macaulay
from the 19th century? And if it is Lord
Macaulay from the 19th century, what is
his legacy and how is it still prevalent
in India today?
Are we explaining that to the people?
So, these slogans, etc., we can keep
doing that forever.
But, at the end of the day, question is
the question is how are you going to
make it happen?
The people won't make it happen. The
people have no idea that they are even
colonized. So, there we have it.
Al-Ghanib says,
"Why What do you think on big companies
world over heavily investing in
promoting DEI?
It doesn't necessarily boost
productivity. Business is all all about
return on investment. In fact, priority
to DEI over merit may adversely impact
quality."
Let me just
Google DEI for the sake of the audience.
What is diversity, equ- equity, and
inclusion?
Principles and initiatives focusing
focused on creating fair and welcoming
environments in workplaces and other
organizations.
Diversity means uh
refers to wide range of backgrounds and
identities. Equity means fair treatment
and access for all. And inclusion is
about creating a culture where everyone
feels a sense of belonging. The goal is
to blah blah blah blah blah. Okay,
that's DEI. It's all about inclusivity
and equity and in diversity. You know,
you need to have a token black person.
You need to have a token yellow person.
You need to have a token brown person.
And everybody else can be something
else. And they must have one gay person,
one person with a disability, one person
with red hair, one person with blue
eyes, one with green eyes, one with
yellow eyes, one with brown eyes.
Uh one sig- 30% should be left-handed.
70% should be right-handed. All that
nonsense. That is DEI.
And everybody must get a a calm,
nurturing environment.
This Everybody should have a safe space
to work in. It's We're talking about
Twitter
before Elon Musk took took over.
Girl power, women power, everybody gets
free lunches, everybody gets their nails
done three times a day. You can work
from home as long as you want. You can
come in and spend 30 minutes doing some
coding and then the rest of the day do
whatever. That's all that thing.
What does it do? It destroys
productivity.
Business is all about ROI. I completely
agree.
In business there is no the concept of
work-life work-life balance doesn't
exist.
Work-life balance is nice if you are an
employee
who works in an organization that is not
very
ambitious.
And and work-life balance is okay if you
have no ambition as a person personally.
You know, you just want to have a safe
job. You will put in your 40 hours a
week and you will do the same thing
every day. You'll get your paycheck and
go back home. That's it. But you will
never be promoted. You will never be
advanced. Whatever. You will never work
in the cutting edge of anything.
So, business, if you want to innovate,
if you want to be at the cutting edge of
business, if you want to be successful
in business, you have to ditch this
entire concept of work-life balance, of
DEI, diversity, equity, inclusivity, all
that nonsense. Only hire the best
people. Only hire the people who are the
willing to work like the hardest. If you
look at the culture in SpaceX, if you
see the culture in Tesla,
you will have people working 90 100 or
110 hours a week.
Okay. Elon Musk, what he did does from
time to time, he orders a surge. Let's
say you have a rocket that is planned to
see that today is what what's the date
today? Today is the 30th of November,
right? Last day of November November
2025.
Let's say there's a rocket planned
rocket launch planned for the 1st of
February, 2026.
So, now I am at SpaceX and I'm I'm about
to go home and Elon Musk comes in.
He says, "Why is no one working?
Why is the rocket not in good shape?
Get all hands on board." He calls up
everybody, all the managers, they fly in
workers from God knows where. He says,
"Okay, today is Sunday night. By Tuesday
morning, the rocket needs to be ready
for launch."
It's physically impossible, but he makes
it happen. Nobody sleeps, people work
three shifts, four shifts, whatever.
Workers coming from wherever else in the
country, they're flown in.
And everybody makes it happen by
Monday
by Tuesday morning or Tuesday evening.
The rocket is ready for launch.
That's how you get things done.
So, it's not for everybody. It's not for
people who are mediocre.
It's only for the the 1% of the 1% but
that's the only way you will get ahead
in business, etc. And DEI doesn't work
there.
Only merit, only the best people can be
hired. So, I don't know if all big
companies world over are heavily
investing in promoting DEI.
A lot of American companies do it in a
token manner that we promote DEI, blah
blah, but these days it's even that is
not being
not
being touted that much anymore, right?
Uh it was a very big deal during the
Biden era. Now that Trump is back in
power, no one's talking about DEI. I
have I have not noticed anyone talking
about DEI the last few months.
So, DEI is actually a killer of
productivity. It's a killer of ambition.
And yeah, uh if you prioritize DEI, it's
going to affect productivity, it's going
to affect quality, it's going to impact
quality, it's going to impact
everything. It's going to impact your
your um
your revenues and so so much more.
Your competitiveness.
So, yep, that's the deal.
Prathap Adnan says, "Have you checked
the Y-DNA heat map website? And shall we
make our own team of admix analysis
since data is available and can be
analyzed in in Linux?"
I have not checked a Y-DNA heat map
website. What what is that? Let me
quickly take a look at that. What's this
Y-DNA heat map website? Y-DNA
heat map. What's the deal?
Which website are we referring to?
Let's see this. The first result in the
search
uh results.
Okay, it's not opening.
Okay, it's open. What do we have? So,
let's zoom into this place. What do we
get here? Uh okay, I need to search for
a specific haplogroup. Let's say we look
for H R1A.
All right, what do we get?
What do we get? Show it. Let's see.
It's taking its own sweet time.
Okay, I think it's going to take some
time and the page is died.
Right, so I haven't checked this.
Um
is it something important? Is it does it
have some new information that's
relevant?
See, uh
there's
when it comes to the Aryan invasion
migration thing, etc.
Genetics is not going to provide answers
to us.
There is no such thing as a pure race,
pure lineage, pure whatever.
I I wonder what my ancestries are like,
from what parts of the world I have
ancestry.
Does it matter?
The the central question in the Aryan
invasion migration tourism picnic myth,
the central question or the central
claim is that Hinduism and Sanskrit came
from outside of India. Now, can that be
proved or disproved?
That's the thing. The have I DNA heat
map, etc. is going to come and go and it
will show all kinds of things. A trickle
of this lineage from here and trickle of
that from here and the Yamnaya have this
and okay, big deal. I am interested in
the origin of Sanskrit and Hinduism.
That's all.
Was the Rigveda
written
in in the 2nd century BC or the 7th
century BC? When when was it written?
And where was it written? That that sort
of thing.
Uh shall we make our own team of admix
analysis since data is available and can
be analyzed in Linux?
Well, if you have the resources to do
that, you can do it. I personally will
not have the time to be involved in such
a thing because I have my own projects
that are going on right now.
And those take all of my time. But if
you have the time and the bandwidth
to do that, well,
that'd be great.
If you can,
you can certainly go ahead and do that,
right?
Vishal Nath says, "Indian literature
exerted profound global effects,
Upanishads on the pre-Socratic monists,
Greek digestion of Nastika Nastika
thought, Latin and Arab digestion of
Siddhantas and Jesuit
transmission of calculus and Yogacara
Zen."
Yeah, no question about it, but uh
Indian literature doesn't ever get the
credit for any of this, right?
Everybody has absorbed ideas, concepts,
etc. from India,
absorbed and digested those and
presented all of that as their own
thought.
Whether it is the Greeks, whether it is
the Europeans, whether it's the Arabs.
The Arabs actually were
the most honorable of all. They did do
all this destruction, devastation of
India. No, the Turks did that actually.
The Turks did that. But the Arabs were
the beneficiaries of all this knowledge
that came from India, from the Indian
universities and libraries, which was
all translated from Sanskrit into Arabic
and Persian by various translators like
Al-Biruni, Al-Khwarizmi, etc. And they
were very clear that all this knowledge
comes from India. And they
you know,
the title of the books they wrote, the
titles of the books they wrote made it
very clear this was Indian knowledge.
Kitab al-Hisab al-Hind and so on.
So, the Arabs were very honorable at
least in in this matter. But the
Europeans who got the knowledge from the
Arabs, they ported it as Arabic
knowledge or their own knowledge,
European knowledge. For example,
for centuries, for thousands of years,
forever, the Europeans did not have any
understanding of mathematics, right?
Then suddenly in the same year of two
months apart, Newton
in England and Leibniz in Germany,
just a few months apart from each other,
both independently discovered calculus.
How does that happen?
What a joke.
It came from India.
And you had these Jesuits,
the most um
advanced thieves in the world.
The thieves of the of the Vatican
church.
So, they were
they were um
they were priests who were trained in
science and they were trained in theft.
So, they would go to various parts of
the world, steal knowledge, bring it
back, and then it would be used by the
Europeans and it would be ported as
European knowledge.
So, yeah, that's been going on for a
very long time. And what we need to do
is that we need to identify what
knowledge has been taken from where and
we need to document all of that. That's
what needs to happen. And that's a
process that I think has already
started.
Greek says, "Do you think that Indian
culture and dharmic principles limit us,
preventing us from behaving as
aggressively as the Europeans do?" Yes.
Is that a good thing? Is that a bad
thing? Well, it's good as well as bad.
See, I'll tell you.
The Europeans
are descendants
of the various clans that were expelled
from the Indian subcontinent
in the aftermath of the Battle of the 10
Kings.
Those clans that were defeated by King
Sudas were expelled out of India
permanently.
And they went and settled in Central
Asia.
Eventually of with they would have made
all the their way all the way into
Europe.
And one of these clans would have been
the
what are now called the Yamnaya.
Right? The utterly barbaric Easterners
who rampaged across Eurasia
and replaced genetically all European
males.
So,
they
most likely came from India.
Right? But their actions were definitely
not dharmic.
The actions were genocide, right?
So, those are not the dharmic actions.
So, once you
hit dharma, you give up dharma, you can
do anything you want.
That's how you That's how you conquer
the world.
So, those were the ancestors of the
Europeans. And the Europeans have
behaved in very rapacious ways in the
past 500 years, completely adharmic
ways.
So, what does it mean for us?
Is our culture is our do our dharmic
principles do these limit us?
Do they prevent us from acting and
behaving aggressively as the Europeans
do? To some extent they do.
Uh Indians, you know that we have never
colonized anyone. We have we have
invaded various parts of the world. For
example, Rajendra Chola invaded West
Southeast Asia. He invaded Srivijaya.
But he did not conduct genocide there.
He did not colonize
these parts of Southeast Asia. He did
not extract all the value out of there.
He did nothing of the of the sort.
He simply reset
the world order in this in this entire
part of the world. That's what he did.
So, Indians have never
been colonizers. We have never been
genociders. We have never been
extractive.
And
perhaps that limits us. Perhaps that
prevents us from becoming as great,
let's say, as the Europeans have become.
So, what should we do?
Should we give up our principles and
then take on the world?
That's a question.
I suppose it's possible to conquer the
world even without shedding our
principles. It's possible, but you know,
if you shed all your principles, if you
shed all of that, then it gives you
unlimited options. So, it kind of does
limit us. It does, right?
Yeah.
Silent Soul says, "In dilemma.
22 done BA. 22 done BA.
Dad's advice, primary teachers diploma.
Month later, college wants me regularly
present.
I want to prepare for competitive exams.
What to do?" Okay, that's a lot of
information.
22 In the year 2022, you did a BA. You
got a bachelor's degree. Your dad's
advice is get yourself a diploma and
become a primary school teacher or
something.
Primary teachers diploma. So, your dad
has these expectations that you should
become a primary teacher, get a diploma
in that.
Uh month later, college wants me to
regularly be present. Okay.
You want to prepare for a competitive
exam. What to do?
Competitive exams. Okay, some
competitive exams. But the college wants
to be regularly present. So, you you are
being pulled in three directions. Your
dad wants you to do teachers diploma.
College wants you to be present here all
the time. And you want to go in this
direction.
Three different directions you have.
You want to go here. College pulls you
here. Dad pulls you there.
What should you do?
What should you do? So, you already have
a BA.
Um
you want to prepare for competitive
exams, which means that you have higher
ambitions, higher aspirations.
College wants you to be regularly
present. Dad says primary school
diploma.
See, primary teachers diploma. I think
primary teachers diploma is a very low
ambition thing, isn't it?
Uh you know, parents generally want to
play safe.
You know, beta, get yourself a nice job,
safe job. At least you will have a
proper salary.
You will not be super rich or whatever,
but at least you will not be broke. That
sort of thing.
So,
that's what your dad wants. That's
That's what I'm understanding.
Uh and college wants you to be regularly
present. You want to prepare. What
should you do?
See, I suppose you can do a primary
teachers diploma even after 2 years,
right? So, tell your dad, "Give me 2
years. I want to try this thing. 2
years, 3 years, whatever. If it doesn't
work out, I'll go for a primary teachers
diploma and do it." So, that deals with
dad. Now, college wants you to be
present, but you want to prepare for
competitive exams. What to do?
I suppose you'll have to juggle that.
Get some
attendance in college and then spend
your time doing competitive exams if it
is possible. Otherwise, I'm not sure
about that how it works.
Otherwise, finish your college degree,
then do competitive exams, which may
waste more time.
Yeah, you're going to have to find your
the right amount of time for call to
spend on college and competitive exams.
Uh college
you already have a BA, right? So, what
are you doing in college?
So, I I think I don't have sufficient
information also. But I would say that
try and
convince your dad to give you a 2 3
years for your competitive exams. Yeah,
that should be possible. Shivansh says,
"Please search on ChatGPT or any LLM.
Which is the one empire that has fought
fought the most battles in the India in
the past 1,000 years and still continues
to live?" Okay, let us ask Google's LLM,
shall we? Oopsie daisy, what happened
there?
Let's find Google. Where is Google? I
lost Google.
All right.
So, let's So, Google has its own LLM,
right? So, which
is the one empire
that has fought
most battles
battles in India in past 1,000
years
and still exists?
Okay, what's it What is it?
What will Google's AI say?
It's complex. It involves Okay, I
understand what the complexities are.
The British Empire.
The one global empire that fought vast
that fought a vast number of
battles in India whose core state still
exists is the British Empire, now the
UK. Still exists um
It says the UK.
Okay. So, what's your point?
So, the UK is no longer an empire. I
don't agree with that. I don't agree
with
Google's AI, whatever it is. Is it
Gemini? Whatever it is.
I don't agree with what it says. The UK
no longer exists as an empire.
It's the US that has taken over the the
mantle of the British Empire.
So, the British Empire fought battles in
in the Indian subcontinent and it no
longer exists, but it does exist in the
shape in form of the American Empire.
So, that's where we are. All right.
Okay, what's the next question?
Where are we?
This is by WBR.
Have you seen the comparison between
Ukraine's pre- and post-war demographic
demographic pyramid? Absolute disaster.
Does it have any future? Will it cease
to exist?
So, I'm aware of what's happened to
Ukraine.
Ukraine's demography has been
devastated.
Uh most young males are dead.
About 30% of Ukraine's population has
collapsed has disappeared.
Let's Let's take a look at what you're
saying here.
Uh
Ukraine uh come on.
Ukraine demographic
pyramid.
2021.
What's it say? What's it say? Show me.
Show me. Here we are.
Ukraine demographic pyramid uh So, you
have this situation in 2021.
Now, what's it look like in 2025?
Absolute disaster.
So, more females than males.
Demographics of Ukraine, which year is
this?
Um
This is
impact on of the war.
2023. You can already see that young
people have disappeared.
Right?
Males, females. Female surplus
significant you have.
Do we have male surplus? I doubt it.
So, essentially, the deal is that
Ukraine has been demographically
devastated. Young men are
almost extinct in Ukraine.
Does Ukraine have a future?
Uh yes.
Hard to say. Looks like it's going to be
very difficult for Ukraine to survive
demographically when all your young male
males are dead.
Of course, children still exist.
But what happens going forward is going
to be a pretty tough uh
ask for Ukraine to survive
demographically long term.
My your top five states that can help
make India tourism superpower. My top
five: Rajasthan, Kerala, Uttarakhand,
Meghalaya, UP.
I would not say I would not give you any
five top states. I think every state in
India has incredible
things to offer from a touristic
perspective.
UP definitely
lots
even a union territory like Ladakh
has so much to offer from a touristic
perspective.
Even Manipur is so incredibly beautiful
not just from a natural beauty
perspective, but also from a cultural
perspective.
But it's been devastated by what's
what's happening right now, right?
Every state has the potential to to make
India superpower.
Every state.
My question is why don't the states take
it seriously? Why doesn't each state of
India have one
world-class museum?
Why can't every state have just one
world-class museum
that showcases the state's 10,000-year
heritage and history?
Why don't we have it?
What kind of people are are ruling
India?
That's what you need to ask yourselves.
Why doesn't every state have a
world-class culinary institute
that showcases
and develops the state's
unique set of cuisines? Why don't you
have it?
Every state has the potential to be a
tourism superpower and make India the
global tourism superpower.
But the politicians are simply not
concerned.
Sad.
Ganapathy says, "Was Israel actually
attempting a genocide or ethnic
cleansing in Gaza? You certainly don't
have to flatten an entire city just to
kill terrorists."
Is Israel or was Israel attempting
a genocide or ethnic cleansing in Gaza?
Well, you see the problem Israel faces
is this. They
Okay.
See, it's like this.
This
Israel-Palestine thing has existed for a
long time, right?
The Palestinians want
self-determination.
So, Israel gave them that.
It gave them autonomy in the West Bank.
It gave them autonomy in Gaza.
It evacuated these regions, gave them
autonomy there.
You They
Israel allowed the people of Gaza to
elect their own government.
Who did they elect?
Hamas.
Right? So, Israel tried its best to
implement a two-state solution
for the people of for the so-called
Palestinian people. The Palestinians
went ahead with terrorism. They elected
Hamas in Gaza.
Hamas went ahead and stockpiled all
these rockets, all this arms,
ammunition. They constructed tunnels all
under Gaza.
Tunnels that that that open up into
hospitals and schools.
And everybody supports terrorism in
Gaza.
When the October
attack happened in Israel, the terrorist
attack had happened in Israel.
It wasn't just Hamas fighters who did
the killings. It was Palestinians who
were working as helpers or workers or
whatever in Israeli territory who also
participated in this. All these
Palestinians
want the Israelis dead.
You give them a chance, they'll
slaughter Israelis.
Now, even if Israel doesn't want to
affect the so-called civilians,
how do they
neutralize terrorists who are hiding in
tunnels under hospitals, under schools?
They deliberately choose hospitals,
schools, and all these places to have
tunnels. So, eventually you can do it
and it'll take forever, it'll never
work, or you just flatten everything.
I think Israel has lost patience and
they have said they've said that we're
going to flatten everything. If you
people survive, that's your good for
you.
If you don't, that's your problem. We
gave you the chance
and you guys went ahead with terrorism.
Now, you pay the price. You pay the
consequences. Yeah?
Because when it comes to the
Palestinians, how does Israel know who
is a terrorist and who is not?
Essentially, they all are.
Now, when the bombs fall, they claim
victimhood.
But when they see an Israeli being
killed on on TV or whatever, even the
little children cheer.
They're all terrorists.
And this is the approach we need to have
with Pakistan actually.
Instead of us having bleeding hearts for
the goddamn Palestinian terrorists,
that's what I would say. So, I
completely support Israel in this
matter. You cannot
be soft-hearted with terrorists.
Okay, that's how I see it. You can
agree, disagree, whatever, that's that's
entirely up to you. But that's how I see
it.
Why do Asian ethnicities of Russia like
Buryats, Tuvans have a higher TFR than
Slavic and other European white
ethnicities? Is it due to low
urbanization? It could be because of
that. See,
the various Asiatic ethnicities, let's
say Mongolic, Tunguscan, Tuvan
ethnicity, etc. ethnicities, Buryats,
Yakuts,
um
Chuvash,
all those people, the Tatars.
These folks, they all live
in the eastern central and eastern parts
of of Russia, the Asiatic parts of
Russia. Uh which typically is villages,
it's farmland, it's forests, and all
that.
And if you're living in a farm, the more
children you have,
the more hands you have to to help you
out on the farm. But if you live in a
city, the entire economic situation is
different. The economic paradigm is
different. In if you're living in a
city, each child is a mouth to feed.
It's it's you need education, you need
to provide for education, you need to
provide health care, all that stuff. And
everything is super expensive if you're
living in a city.
So, it becomes a net drain on your on
your on your finances. But if you are
living in the farm, if you're living in
forest, etc., the more children you
have, the more hands you have to work.
So, it's it's a totally different
economic paradigm in farmlands, in in
rural areas.
And yeah, so that's why
that that clearly is one of the
significant causes for the people
Russians who live outside of
metropolitan areas, especially in the
Far East of Russia, etc., why they have
higher TFRs, definitely.
Arub Shah says, "I was very upset to
hear that there isn't a single highly
prestigious Indian physics journal. Our
highest impact factor is 2.4. I want to
establish one. Could you give me further
guidance?"
You want to establish a high impact
physics journal.
You want guidance from me.
Look, if I knew how to do that, I would
have done it myself, right?
How do you establish a prestigious
physics journal?
What is the factor that determines the
prestige of
a physics journal?
You need to have high-quality,
high-impact research being published in
your physics journal, which means that
you need the top physicists of the world
to publish in your journal.
Why will top physicists publish in
a specific journal? They will publish in
a journal first of all if it already has
a great reputation, if other great
physicists have published there. For
example, there's something called the
Annalen der Physik where Einstein, etc.
have published in the past. So, yeah,
it's prestigious. So, you want to you
want to publish there. Secondly, the
journal should have a great editorial
team.
And they should have great referees
who will, you know, referee your your
paper to the highest possible
to the highest possible quality.
Um and obviously it has to be a
prestigious
nation and so on.
So, that's how you establish the
prestige of a journal. Now, let's say
you want to establish a journal, you can
establish a journal journal, but how
will you induce the top physicists of
the world to publish in your journal?
You're going to have to set up a
committee of editors. You're going to
have to set up reviewers, anonymous
reviewers, and so on
who have to be top-quality physicists
themselves. How will you recruit these
people?
Right? It's easier said than done.
If it was easy, I would have done it
myself, but it's very difficult. So,
I can certainly go ahead and talk to
various physicists in the country
and say that we let us set up a journal
together.
How many of them will be willing to do
it? You already have something called
Pramana in India. I'm not sure what
Pramana is up to these days, but I have
known people who published in Pramana
personally.
So,
a prestigious journal is possible in a
only in in a country where you already
have top-quality physics research being
done. In India, there is no top-quality
physics research being done. That's why
it's not possible for India to have a
top-quality, highly prestigious physics
journal. It's not possible.
So, you see, Arub,
I completely
I I I feel you.
I've been there.
But when you are in a country where
there's no significant physics research
being done,
where you have a terrible, third-rate
education system and academic system,
it's not possible
for a prestigious, high-quality journal
to exist here. Even if you set up the
best journal with the best editors and
best reviewers,
why will top physicists publish in a
country where nothing is is happening?
Why?
The problem lies deeper. It's not the
problem of the people who are running
journals. And you also have another
problem in India, predatory, parasitical
journals.
I get these emails from these random all
the time. Please publish your research
in our journal.
Small publishing fee.
Essentially, what they are saying is
that you pay us this much money and your
research is guaranteed to be published.
What's the quality going to be like? So,
India is one of the top bases for all
these predatory and parasitical journals
who are minting money by having
third-rate research being published in
India. So, India has developed this
reputation, this negative reputation
of being the hub of so many of these
predatory journals.
And what is the government of India
doing about this?
Nothing.
And then if you set up a new journal,
most people will assume that you are
going to be another parasitical
predatory journal.
So, that is the problem.
What guidance can I give you, Arav?
I'm assuming that you have a physics
background.
What guidance can I give you?
Go ahead with your physics career,
publish high-quality research in the
best journals that you can find. That's
all I can tell you.
Without the government cracking down on
all these problems, nothing's going to
change in India. We individuals can't
change things.
It's not going to be possible.
Bhaskar Bandit says, "Delhi pollution
heat map from satellite so shows a lot
of parali burning in Pakistan. Is it
part of war by other means along with
our own issues, of course?"
I think
uh the farmers in Pakistan, they have
their own way of doing
doing things.
I don't think they're doing it with the
objective of polluting Delhi and
polluting parts of India. It's just that
um
once their crops have been harvested,
all the stubble that's left, what's
called parali or whatever it's called,
the stubble that is left, um instead of
wasting time cutting it off and
processing it, just burn it, right? If
you burn it, it leaves behind ash, which
is rich in minerals,
which fertilizes the soil.
So, you're going to burn everything,
it's going to
be a nuisance for a couple of days, and
then you have,
you know, clean land with lots of
fertile ash on it. So, you can go ahead
with the next crop. So, I don't think
it's part of a war by other means or
whatever. A lot of this stubble burning
also happens within our own territories.
I mean, if you take off from New Delhi
or land in New Delhi, either at dawn or
at dusk or at night
in the wintertime,
okay, you're going to see a lot of fires
burning all around, especially west of
Delhi, north and west of Delhi, Punjab
Haryana region.
Right?
So, that's that's what it is. A lot of
that could be coming from Pakistan, but
much some of it comes from India as
well.
And I don't think it's uh
it's war by other means. It's just the
way they've been doing things for a long
time. Okay.
Sagar Gare says, "Why did the United
States continue with a second attack on
August 9, 1945 instead of stopping after
the one on August 6?"
Are you talking about cyberattacks?
There was no cyber warfare in 1945. Was
it You're talking about the nuclear
tests on Japan are you talking about?
Let's see what happened on August 6,
1945, just to reconfirm.
August
August 6, 1945, what happened?
Hiroshima.
So, yes, August 6, 1945, the United
States tested a nuclear weapon on the
people of Hiroshima
in Japan.
And
3 days later, subsequent to that, they
tested another nuclear device on the
people of Nagasaki in Japan.
So, why did the US conduct a second test
in Nagasaki after the first test in
Hiroshima?
Well, the Japanese empire had not
surrendered.
So, after Hiroshima, Japan did not
surrender.
So, after the Americans did Nagasaki,
and they said, "Now you surrender,
otherwise we'll do a third one." So,
that's when Japan surrendered. That's
the simple
reasoning.
Amisha says, "Your views on modern-day
feminism and masculinism." I haven't
heard of this term masculinism, but
feminism, yeah, I know feminism.
Modern-day feminism is uh
See,
feminism
it emerged for the right reasons.
It emerged in the United States in the
19th century, roughly.
And why did feminism have to emerge from
this place? It's because women had
second-class citizen status.
They did not have property rights, they
were the property of their husbands. Uh
they did not have any voice in society,
they did not have any role to play in
society, they did not have property
rights, they did not have legal rights,
and they did not have
right to property and
they were second-class citizens, they
were the property of their husbands, and
so on. They were very badly abused
and marginalized in society, in American
society. It's all because of uh what we
have discussed in the past few days, you
know, how uh the Christian doctrine
Christian ideology, Christian religion
treats women.
So, that's why feminism had to
happen so that women could get basic
rights like equal rights, right to vote,
uh right to own property, and so on.
But then, from the 1950s and '60s
onwards, feminism was hijacked by the
left.
And then feminism became a supremacist
religion kind of thing.
So, modern-day feminism is not about
equal rights, it's about superior
rights.
It's about
putting men down and making women
superior to men.
So, that's what you see in in societies
like the United States. The United
States has become a gynocentric society.
Women like are the bullies now, and the
men are the oppressed.
That's what's happened in the US.
Perhaps it serves them right, whatever.
My point is,
feminism
it
it belongs in a certain context.
It belongs in the context of nations
with Abrahamic perspectives that have
historically and perhaps perhaps even
now oppressed women.
When you talk about non-Abrahamic
societies like ours, polytheistic
societies, with a very different
approach to the roles of the two
genders,
feminism doesn't belong here. Feminism
doesn't have any relevance here.
We have never oppressed women.
We have never marginalized women and
whatever.
So, feminism has no place actually in
India. But because of Western education
and all that all this nonsense, feminism
is now a thing in India also, women's
rights and all that. Women have never
been deprived of rights in India.
In some cases in in in certain roles,
women have more rights than men and some
So, it's a it's We are a different
civilization. And we are not an
oppressive civilization, we have never
oppressed women. So, my
the way I see it, feminism has no place
in India.
Yeah, that's how I see it. And feminism
is is
today modern feminism is is all about,
you know,
making women superior to men.
And essentially taking revenge for the
patriarchy, that sort of thing.
Which is is nasty. We don't need such
things in society. That's That's how I
see it.
Okay. King Ritwik says, "What
infrastructure
No, sorry. What development does
Arunachal need so that we can shut up
China? Should we focus on tourism,
roads, and infrastructure in Tawang,
Mechuka Valley, Mechuka Valley,
Itanagar?"
What
If you want to shut up China,
it's not about shutting up China. Please
understand this. This is not about a war
of words where you shut somebody up.
This is about the real and present
danger that China,
which is four times more powerful than
India, can perhaps make a move on
Arunachal Pradesh and annex annex the
territory.
It's not about shutting up China.
It's about preventing such an
eventuality from becoming
reality.
That's what needs to happen. So, how do
we make it happen? We make it happen by
augmenting our military muscle.
That's what needs to happen.
We need to augment our capabilities,
military capabilities.
Whether it is the number of missiles
that we have, the kinds of missiles, the
types of missiles that we have. Do we
have bunker buster ammunition? Do we
have various kinds of ballistic and
cruise missiles? Do we have subsonic
cruise missiles? We do have supersonic
cruise missiles. What about hypersonic
cruise missiles? Do we have sufficient
numbers of aircraft squadrons? Do we
have sufficient high-quality aircraft,
maybe fifth-generation aircraft, maybe
4.5-generation aircraft? Do we have all
of these things? Do we have the right
amount the right number of satellites
that we need to cover the entire Tibet
region and beyond Arunachal and whatnot
to know exactly what's happening day or
night along the border, the line of
actual control? Do we have have all of
these things? Do we have a sufficiently
strong force posture south of the
India-Tibet border in the mountainous
regions? Do we have the ability to to
deploy
in 6 hours? Or does it will it take us 6
days to deploy our armed forces when we
give after we give the order? How
rapidly can we deploy our forces in
forward positions? Do we have a cold
start capability uh along Arunachal? And
then you ask yourself, do we have enough
roads to all those things?
That's what we need to do.
Roads, yeah, sure, we need more roads,
etc.
And that's also
uh a work in progress.
Okay. Adi Ayus says, "Just clicking on
share and commenting once after the live
stream ends will boost the channel
growth a lot. Request to viewers, thank
you. Well, Adi Ayush, thank you so much.
I request all viewers to share
and comment after the live stream ends
and please like, share, and subscribe.
Yeah, I never I never ask for any of
these things, but yeah, please do that.
So, Adi Ayush, thank you so much for
for once for reminding me to to remind
the viewers of this. Please do that. It
will help the channel a lot.
As you know all know, my channel is now
capped at 248 249,000
948 or 949,000 subscribers. YouTube or
somebody in YouTube has decided that my
subscribers should not grow beyond that.
Uh so, anyway, if you
do these things, then maybe it'll help.
So, please do that. Please help out.
Thank you. Thank you so much.
All right, next. Biju Saikia says,
"Indian politicians love to call
themselves nationalists, but it's
opposite when it comes to US leaders.
How did it become such a negative word
in Europe?"
Uh
Nationalism is bad, patriotism is good,
that sort of thing, right?
I still don't know what's the difference
between nationalism and patriotism.
Apparently, nationalism is good bad
because it gives rise to fascism and and
whatnot.
So, if you're European, nationalism is
bad. I don't
Is it a bad thing to do to love your
country?
Is it a bad thing to
to want your country to prosper, to
progress, etc.?
Is it a bad thing?
Or should you want all countries to
prosper and progress? Does it work like
that in the world?
It's never worked that way in the world.
Everyone has wanted their country to
progress prosper and progress, and
nations always compete, as we know. Look
at what the US is doing. Look at its
actions. It's These are
hyper-competitive actions. Look at what
the Chinese are doing.
Hyper-competitive. So, if the top powers
do that, why should the other powers not
also play the same game?
So,
you see,
how did this become such a negative word
in Europe? It's after the Second World
War that nationalism becomes a bad thing
because nationalism gave us gave rise to
the Nazi ideology and fascist ideology
and so on.
Um and after the Second World War, when
it comes to Western Europe, the United
States became the major power in Western
Europe. It became the hegemonic power in
Western Europe, and it did not want any
of these nations to have new seeds or
sprouts of nationalism and patriotic
thought. So, it said, you know,
create a EU, dissolve your borders,
dissolve your currency. Let's have a
common currency, that sort of thing,
which eventually happened.
And yeah, no nationalism.
So, that's how it became a negative word
because it's associated with uh
fire far-right ideologies.
And Indian politician Yeah, that's
right.
But when it comes to American leaders,
we today you have the slogan, right?
Make America great again.
That's a very nationalistic slogan, by
the way. So,
Hyphen says, "Been watching you since
2021." Well, thank you. That's when I
started the
you know, regularly posting on the
channel. So, thank you so much.
"You changed my life in a way. Wow. Wow,
okay. I can think more clearly now.
Thank you. Miss your science episodes,
by the way."
All right. First of all, thank you so
much. I really appreciate uh
your having been a long-time viewer.
Thank you so much. I'm glad that I could
make could have some kind of a positive
impact in your life.
Um
And when it comes to the science
episodes, we're going to do a space
special next week.
Okay?
So, next week we'll do a space special,
maybe science special, in which you can
have space also.
So, let's bring that back
once in a while. I'll do that.
Anyway, thank you so much, sir. Thank or
ma'am. Thank you.
Chirag Srinath says,
"I have
I have my questions.
What is your opinion on the nuclear
sector being privatized in India that
was announced this week?"
I haven't seen this news. I haven't seen
the announcement. If the nuclear sector
is being privatized in India, well, I
don't think it's necessarily a bad
thing. It's it's a good thing.
Um what does it mean? Let's Let's take a
look at the news so that we understand
what the parameters of this
privatization is private
parameters are.
Uh nuclear sector privatization
India. Let's see. What's it say?
India
Okay, let's see. Times of India. India's
nuclear policy. Prime Minister Modi
announces plans to open nuclear sector
to private players,
pushing next-generation reactors and
innovation.
Uh boost energy security, technology
advance advancement, increase nuclear
power capacity significantly by 2047. A
new bill will be introduced to
facilitate this major policy shift.
Follows the successful opening of the
space sector to private players.
Um We are moving towards the nuclear
sector as well. We are laying the
foundation, etc.
Create opportunities in small modular
modular reactors, advanced reactors, and
nuclear innovation.
Um
We have an ambitious goal of scaling
India's nuclear power power capacity to
100 gigawatts by 2047. Right now, it's
8.8 gigawatts. So, more than 10 times
increase, okay?
Uh what else do we have? Private company
The Atomic Energy Act 1962 bars private
companies, even state governments, from
participating in this
sector.
Okay, so that's It doesn't say much. It
says that
we're going to open up the private We're
going to open up the sector to private
players, private industry.
Well, good. See, if you want to be a
player in this industry, let's say you
want to build small modular reactors.
You're going to have to invest a few
billion dollars into that.
It's not cheap.
So, it's It's only going to be the
biggest private players who going to be
able to participate in this thing.
Understand that. But it's not I'm not
saying it's a bad thing, you know.
We have
very big
uh
very big uh
players in the Indian uh private sector
who could certainly, you know, take this
forward.
So, it's good, in my opinion.
Without the the private industry getting
involved in this, we can't scale from
8.8 gigawatts to 100 gigawatts. So,
uh I hope this is a great success.
Biju Saikia says, "Why most of humans
became monogamous?"
Um why did humans become monogamous? So
that we have stability in society.
See, about 10,000 or so years ago, we
moved from maybe 15,000 years ago in the
subcontinent, we moved from being
hunter-gatherers
to agriculturalists.
Right?
So, when we were hunter-gatherers, our
populations were very small, and we
lived in very small bands of people.
And in that case, the polygamy, that
sort of thing, could have worked
because, you know, the strongest guy
rules everybody else. Maybe he passes on
his genes and others don't, that sort of
thing.
But when you have settled societies
who settle down in one place,
set up villages and towns and have big
farms, and you have to live together
for your entire lives, you can't have
clashes and strife in in society.
So, for that,
stability in society, you need monogamy.
Maybe kings can be polygamous or
whatever, but most people have to be
monogamous. Otherwise, you're going to
have clashes and fighting and whatnot.
So, I think that's why once you made the
transition from uh hunter-gatherer
lifestyle to sedentary lifestyle and I
pastoral lifestyle, that's where this uh
change happened, and it made sense.
Chirag Srinath says, "Woah
What is the stark difference between Sun
Tzu and Chanakya and the way they shape
policies in China and India, the effect
they have today in the respective
countries?"
See, um I have shown this in the past.
Where's the Arthashastra?
Okay, I'm not sure where it is. I'll
have to look into it.
One second. Give me a second.
You see, this is the Art of War by Sun
Tzu.
As you can see, it's this flimsy little
book.
Flimsy. How many pages? Let me see.
Um
63 pages in this version, which is the
full version of the of the Art of War.
It's a flimsy little book of stratagems.
What is a stratagem, and what's the
difference between a stratagem and a
strategy?
A stratagem is a trick.
Excuse me. It's a clever trick.
A strategy is a totally different thing.
Sun Tzu's book is a book of stratagems.
It's a book of clever tricks.
Chanakya's Arthashastra is this massive
book. I'm I'm sure
I've got it somewhere here, but the
point is,
it's this massive book. It's about how
to run an empire.
Completely different thing. You can't
compare the Arthashastra with this
thing, this little thing.
Okay?
So, um
huge difference, massive difference.
Sun Tzu is a set of tricks.
Has Sun Tzu's shaped
Has the Art of War shaped policy in
China massively? No.
China has not been influenced merely by
Sun Tzu. It is the West that has been
enamored with Sun Tzu.
Sun Tzu is one of the texts in China.
China has been more influenced
influenced by Confucius, Confucian
uh
ideology, teachings, etc.
They've been influenced by various
Chinese thinkers
uh the in warfare and whatnot. Sun Tzu
doesn't really figure that prominently
in Chinese thought.
When it comes to Chanakya
Chanakyan thought obviously has formed
the backbone of India's empires
whether knowingly or unknowingly.
Uh but today Chanakyan thought is absent
in India.
I would say that Pakistan practices
Chanakya Niti better than India today.
Right?
So yeah, that's the thing.
So Sun Tzu and Chanakya are very
different. Their their works are very
different. You can't compare the
Arthashastra with something like
something like Sun Tzu's The Art of War,
little flimsy little book.
So I would encourage everybody to at
least, you know, if you if you're
interested in these things try and read
these things.
Try and see this little book.
I'm sure if you buy it from a roadside
roadside shop you can get it for 50
rupees or something, little tiny little
book. The Arthashastra may be more
expensive, but try and acquire these
books and read them. Try reading them,
right?
Very interesting and very important to
try these things out. Okay.
Do you agree with Musk's claim of Putin
being the richest man?
Uh
I have not Did Musk really claim that? I
haven't seen this claim.
Uh do I think Putin is the richest man?
I don't think he's the richest man.
So yeah. So if Elon Musk has claimed
this, I don't agree with him.
Okay.
Hyphen says, "Can you start a series
where you pick a great man and or a
woman each episode and do a full episode
on Einstein, Newton, etc. Doesn't have
to be a scientist."
Certainly a great uh
great idea. There's so many great ideas
out there that I can implement um
implement.
Yeah, I could make a list of 100 super
influential people, the most
influential people in human history from
my perspective, the top 100. And uh
do an episode on each. I could certainly
do that.
See, right now I have a set of projects
I'm working on, writing projects.
I've been speaking the past 4 5 years,
right? I have written nothing.
I should be the one writing the most
books in this country.
So right now I'm focusing on writing.
Which is why it will not be possible for
me to start these series right now.
The next, let's say, 12 months I'm going
to focus full-time on writing. I'm going
to continue these live streams and all
that.
But until I have a
two or three books out, I'm not going to
start any new big
uh project like this.
If I can find the time, I could do it,
but I don't think if I'm writing three
books in a year, which is the goal, then
it's going to be possible at this point
in time. But it's a great thought, it's
a great
idea
for a series.
And it's something I should certainly
do. So thank you so much for the
suggestion.
And I think it's one of the best
suggestions I've got.
So thank you, and I will do it sooner or
later. So thank you so much.
Biju Saikia says, "Have you ever read
any of Stephen King's books?"
In 2002
I spent a few months in the United
States.
I was working as a cyber
Okay?
And it was pretty strenuous work.
12 hours plus a day you're working.
But whenever I got some time, I would go
to a shop called Borders.
I don't think Borders even exists
anymore. Used to be a bookshop.
And over there there was a sale and I
acquired this big fat book
called Bag of Bones by Stephen King.
Hardcover.
It was on sale and I got it for $5 or
something.
And over the course of a week or
something whenever I could snatch some
time I would read that and I finished
the entire book.
And uh
yeah, it's kind of
disturbing in in parts and
it does have creepy moments and stuff.
So yeah, it was a very well-written
book, no question about it. It starts
really slow and then it pulls you in,
that sort of thing, Bag of Bones.
Perhaps Stephen King's best seller or
maybe not, I don't know.
It's the one book I've read. I've also
read some other book more recently, but
I can't remember what it was. So yeah,
I've I've read a couple of his books.
The first one that I do remember very
well is Bag of Bones. I've got it
somewhere in the house.
Right.
Raju
No, Rarun Raj. Okay.
Whatever the name is.
"Should we have banned Google Street
View? Many views are looking bad and
racists are using that as points. Feel
this is regulated in the western world
like Paris only shows clean stuff.
China, Russia, Afghanistan, Egypt, some
Africans don't have it."
Look, if you're a filthy country in some
parts of the country
what's the point of hiding it? I don't
think we should ban Google Street View.
If you want to ban stuff, ban it
entirely.
Look, if you've been to Paris, you will
know
that Paris is mostly super clean.
You go to London, you go to Milan, you
go to Berlin, you go to Frankfurt, you
go to London.
Way cleaner than India.
Right?
And now there are some cities in India
which are super clean also.
For example, if you go to I don't know.
If you go to Surat
in western India
it's way cleaner than, for example,
other other cities in India.
So India also you have some cities that
are super clean.
But if you look at the average situation
in India, it's not very good. And I
mean, if you take Delhi, for example,
the capital city. There are parts of
Delhi that are super clean, super neat,
and there are parts of old Delhi where
you don't want to go because they're not
clean.
So my point is, look, even if you ban
Google Street View, you're going to have
tourists coming to India looking for
those things. They're going to post it
on on YouTube. Now you're going to ban
them, too?
The solution is not banning stuff. The
solution is improving your standards.
Now we can't do it. The government is in
charge of doing it. So my request to the
government
to the governments
is that please get your act together
and do what you're what you're elected
for.
Right?
Okay, Biju Saikia says
"Do you think
horseshoe theory correct?" I don't know
what the horseshoe theory is. Let me try
and Google it. What is a What is the
horseshoe theory?
What is the horseshoe theory? Political
concept suggesting that the extreme left
and extreme right of the political
spectrum are more similar to each other
than the center
like the ends of a horseshoe.
Um
I don't know.
Are the extreme left and the extreme
light right are they similar?
Both tend to be authoritarian, but both
tend to have very different perspectives
on what to do.
So I'm not sure if it's really correct.
I'll have to put obviously put more
thought into this before I can say yes
or no definitively, but it
It it doesn't doesn't look like it's
very correct. Because
both extreme right and extreme left tend
to be super authoritarian, but their
but their ideas, ideologies, and desired
outcomes are very different. So I'm not
sure that that it's correct.
Diden Slonter says
"M MSC physics, addicted to alcohol in
lockdown.
Going far area for drinks.
I have friended local alcoholics.
One day a labor
One day
a labor close alcoholic
broken my leg fingers, bedridden for 2
months.
Should I make a move on him with my
friends as I am now well?"
Okay, so you are MSC physics, you
became addicted to alcohol during the
lockdown.
You go to far away areas for drinks. You
made friends with local alcoholics. One
day
one day a labor close alcoholic broke
your leg fingers, your toes.
And you were bedridden for 2 months. And
you're fine now.
And you are asking whether you should
make a move on him with your friends
because you're you're well now.
I would say, you know what I would say?
Um
What I would recommend is
end your friendships with all alcoholics
and stop doing alcohol
and forget about taking revenge.
Move on.
Put all of this in the past. Put put all
of this behind you. That's what I would
recommend to do.
I know it's easier said than done.
It's easy to give advice, but since you
asked for advice
I I I have a very clear rule. I don't
give advice unless someone asks for it.
But since you're asking for advice, I
would say
end your friendships with all
alcoholics.
If you don't change the kind of people
you're around you hang around with, you
can't change your habits.
So whoever your friends are who are
alcoholics and who are who are keeping
you hooked to alcohol
end your friendships with them.
Break off relations with those people.
Don't
go and make a move on this individual.
Forget about what happened.
Just make it a thing of your past. End
your
relationship with alcohol. Stop drinking
alcohol.
And go get going with your life. That's
what I would recommend you do, sir. All
right? That's my honest, sincere
recommendation to you.
I hope you do well in life, sir.
Please get your act together. All the
best.
Raru Rarun Jar says, "India should block
visas to the guys like Bald and Bankrupt
who only come to India to show bad
things and mint money.
His whole channel promotes hate."
I suppose if there are channels
you know if there are individuals who
only come to India for for for
these negative purposes then those
people should be blacklisted.
There are lots of YouTubers who come to
India and show the good as well as the
bad which I think is fair enough.
Right? But if there are people who only
want to do this
poverty tourism and whatever whatever
this some of the people do those people
should be
blacklisted. I agree with you. So
whoever this person is and I'm sure
there are others too
such people should be blacklisted no
question about that. The Chinese would
not tolerate this neither should we.
Okay why is Japan always fighting Russia
over useless islands but follows orders
from country that literally nuked them?
Your opinion on Anna Chapman's Chapman
spy incident.
Anna Chapman was this Russian lady this
redhead lady who was a spy in something.
I don't remember the the details so
it's been a while. She was imprisoned in
the US and then
exchanged with some other spy who was
from Russia right that sort of thing.
Okay why is Japan fighting Russia over
uses useless islands but follows orders
from the country that literally nuked
them?
The country that literally nuked Russia.
Are they friends with Russia? But I'm
sorry the country that literally nuked
Japan.
That big powerful country is it friends
with Russia or is it enemies with
Russia? It's enemies with Russia right?
And Japan is controlled by the US who is
enemies with Russia.
The US will use Japan to needle Russia.
Doesn't it make logical sense?
You see Japan doesn't merely follow
orders from the United States. Japan has
been under permanent military occupation
by the United States since 1945.
The US has more than 130 permanent
military bases on Japanese soil. What
option does Japan have?
Japan has to do whatever they are told.
So if they are fighting Russia over
useless islands which you see as useless
maybe the Americans are making this
happen.
And maybe the islands are not useless
or maybe there's a whole history behind
that that you are not aware of
which is why you see it as useless.
On my channel
please search in the search box Kuril
Islands
and look up the history of this matter
before calling the islands useless.
All right?
See
when we don't know the history of a
dispute we may think it's a pointless
dispute. Oh it's a bunch of islands.
It's this it's that.
Please try to take the time to
understand the history.
Understand the reason for this dispute
then you will understand that maybe the
islands are not useless maybe they are
very valuable.
All right?
Okay.
Um
Krish Krishai says why has socialism
failed in many countries?
Excuse me.
Why has socialism failed?
Socialism
is destined to fail everywhere.
Because socialism seeks to
achieve equality of outcome
not equality
of opportunities.
That's why it's going to fail.
But one place socialism hasn't failed is
China because it's not really socialism.
See in China there's something called Xi
Jinping thought today which is a
continuation of Maoist Leninist thought
and
Mao Zedong thought and Deng Xiaoping
thought and whatever else thought. Now
it's called Xi Jinping thought which is
an extension and
elaboration of all of that. And if you
study Xi Jinping thought they say that
you know we have to be firm on Chinese
on socialism with Chinese
characteristics etc. But it's not really
socialism anymore.
Uh so socialism is all about equality of
outcomes which doesn't work anywhere.
Which is why it's going to keep on
failing.
Uh Rarura Rarunrajar
says
at what point does geopolitics become
history
and history can be considered to be
geopolitics? What's the time limit? We
discuss discuss internal matters
of other countries when does internal
politics become relevant for
geopolitics?
See geopolitics becomes history
there's no
hard and fast rule.
If I'm discussing something from for
example the 1990s
is that history?
Well technically it's history.
But if you want to discuss the Ukraine
war you would discuss what happened in
the 1990s so it's kind of a continuing
problem.
So it's the boundaries are kind of
vague. It's like the boundary between
classical and quantum physics. I mean I
can actually give you a very clear
definition of where quantum physics
starts but you know
when it okay we'll not give use that
analogy because that's too technical.
The point is
there's no clear delineation of where
geopolitics starts and history ends.
That sort of thing. Maybe 20 30 years
you can take as a rough rough guiding
principle. Yeah.
We discuss internal politics of other
countries when does internal politics
become relevant for geopolitics?
Internal politics of a nation becomes
relevant for geopolitics when it starts
affecting other countries. Simple as
that. There's an election in the US it's
an internal matter
but the regime changes a new president
comes and he changes all the rules of
the game geopolitically well then the
internal matter becomes relevant
geopolitically and globally. You see? So
when internal matters of countries
start becoming external problems for
others that's where
internal politics becomes relevant for
geopolitics.
So yeah that's the deal. So geopolitics
and history I would say 20 30 years as
as a rough yardstick but not necessarily
always going to be correct.
Ansh Devu says
please explain Indian genetics frozen in
time for 1900 years. Does it imply
strictly enforced endogamy caste system
or any other genetic hoax like AIT?
Uh Indian genetics frozen in time for
1900 years who is saying this?
It looks like so when we talk about
endogamy
does it mean the caste system?
Endogamy doesn't mean the caste system.
It means the jati varna system which is
different from the goddamn caste system
that you are taught
and that is now enforced the four
castes.
The jati varna system I think it became
more solidified during the Gupta era.
And that's what that's what genetics
kind of seems to show to some extent.
That we have endogamy among the jatis
that starts sometime around the Gupta
era. See the thing is this
any
any highly functioning society or
civilization is going to be highly
structured and
it's going to be highly structured. It's
going to be stratified.
You know if you look at the Wikipedia
definition of civilization it says
stratified society.
Right?
So when you have a highly ordered
society it means that it's got all these
specializations and and intricate
division of labor.
All the different things and aspects and
goods and services that you need for a
functioning society you will have
lineages
dedicated to that. So one family line or
one or one jati
does for example
a certain kind of industrial practice
or produces maybe manufactures ships.
Somebody else does metal work. Somebody
else does goldsmith work. Somebody else
does textile work. So they will keep all
those things within their clan and they
will not share the secrets of the with
others otherwise they will lose that
competitive advantage.
And that's why they will marry among
each other. That sort of thing. So that
that is something you see in every
civilization every culture in the world.
You see that everywhere.
So it's not a caste system thing or
whatever it just makes sense and now
it's being destroyed.
Uh was it strictly enforced endogamy? It
was like because of societal norms
eventually it became that way. It's not
a genetic hoax. So that is how this
thing happened and that's
inherent
a characteristic of any advanced
society.
Okay WBR says was having a family
conversation about an Indian king
bone kept nearby later YouTube started
recommending shows and videos about
on the king.
Considering that data is stored in the
US does Uncle Sam have the ability to to
create a civil war in India? Now that's
a totally different thing from what
you're saying but it's kind of relevant.
See I've got my phone here.
I'm talking.
It's listening to everything I say. It's
on silent right now.
It listens to everything I say.
You're having intimate connections with
conversations with family or whoever
you've got a phone nearby it's listening
to everything.
It doesn't mean some person is listening
but the system is listening. And if if
it if your conversations have words that
trigger certain flags
it's going to have certain effects.
Maybe you start getting recommendations
about a king maybe something else.
So because of these things because all
of this data is stored in the US whether
it is whatever Android Apple whatever
it means the US
regime has all kinds of information
about everybody in India.
They may have secrets about us and god
knows what else. So if they want to
create a civil war they can do it.
Short answer.
A fast snail, love the name. Do you
foresee any repercussions from the West
post Putin trip?
Depends.
Uh I would expect that the Putin trip
that that President Putin's trip to
India which going to happen soon,
it could perhaps be momentous uh in
uh the context of the India-US
relationship India-Russia relationship
and overall
geopolitics.
If
major new deals uh
are signed by the two countries, maybe
hypothetically the so-called 57 fighter
fifth generation fighter plane, maybe
something else, maybe other kinds of
cooperation, then it's going to
clearly have repercussions from the
West. Right? So, if it makes
India-Russia if it benefits India and
Russia in a big way,
and if it brings the two nations closer
together, the Americans will be upset
about this. And even the Chinese will be
upset about this.
Even the Pakistanis will be upset about
this. Pakistan doesn't matter. Pakistan
just does whatever their masters tell
them, but the US and China will be
upset. So, there there's going to be
repercussions.
So, obviously all of this will be
factored into the calculations of both
Russia and India.
Ganapathy says, was European
colonization
colonialism a Jewish initiative?
Columbus was a Jew.
Uh it was a Jew called Isaac Le Pinto
that that convinced the British Crown to
colonize India.
So, I am not aware of this Isaac Le
Pinto. Let's take a look at this person,
Isaac Le Pinto.
Pinto.
That's interesting.
Isaac Le Pinto was
Portuguese Sephardic Jewish origin.
One of the main investors in the Dutch
East India Company. Okay.
So,
what do we have about this guy?
Um
So, he was a major investor in the Dutch
East India Company.
Not the British
Right?
So, it's it's well known that that that
that various Jewish persons were major
money lenders money lenders etc.
in Europe and they financed many
initiatives of the kingdoms that they
were subjects of.
Many of them would lend money to the
Crown
to finance military expenditures, maybe
or other things or the other projects.
Uh Columbus was a Jew it he may have
been perhaps a Jew, I'm not sure.
So, was all of this European
colonization a Jewish initiative? I I
think it's a little too far-fetched to
say it was a Jew Jewish initiative. The
Jewish were the financiers of many
projects, not merely colonization
projects, but all the other projects
also.
So, I think it's it's uh
a little far-fetched to say that
everything all of this was like a Jewish
initiative all of this that they goaded
the Europeans to go and colonize the
world and destroy the world. I think it
would be a little far-fetched to imagine
that.
Purushottam says,
Virat is the greatest ODI player. What
are my thoughts? Look now, cricket is
super controversial. I am very clear
about where I stand in cricket. I have
been observing cricket since what?
I was never a fan of cricket when I was
a kid, okay?
But I spent a few years in Europe etc.
When I came back to India, everyone
plays cricket and nobody wants to play
football, so I had to learn how to play
cricket.
And nobody was was willing to give me a
bat in my hand, so I had to learn how to
bowl. So, I became a bowler. I became a
pretty good bowler. And I've been
watching cricket
since what? Since the 1990s, early
1990s. And I remember all of all of what
I've watched.
So, is Virat the greatest ODI player?
No.
He's not.
Nah.
Vivian Richards is the greatest ODI
player batsman.
Vivian Richards is the greatest of the
ODI batsman. You have no idea the kind
of bowlers he played against.
Okay. So, I disagree. Virat Kohli, no.
No, thank you.
I'm not saying he's he's not good. He's
great. I have been a great fan of Virat
Kohli.
Especially his captaincy style when he
in the in the in the 2010s.
Especially the way he played against
Australians in Australia, the way he led
the team against Australia.
And his batting, I mean, one of the
greatest of all in Indian batsman, no
question about that. One of the greatest
of all time,
but not the greatest of all time. I
would say Vivian Richards is the
greatest of all time.
And I have seen a lot. So, that is my
perspective. And I'm sure before
Richards there were players that I am
not aware of, I've not seen, but yeah.
Uh VSVS says, what are the biggest
mistakes India is making today that
could haunt us in 2050?
Not reforming the education system. Not
focusing uh
not focusing on research and
development. Not reforming fast enough.
Not focusing on
Excuse me.
Not focusing
on manufacturing sufficiently.
Not focusing on the cutting edge uh
technologies like AI and the space race.
These mistakes could haunt us by 2050.
Right?
The education system has to be reformed
the way I have explained
in episodes what? 29 to 28 to 32
approximately of the Ask Abhijit show.
Nothing is being done.
India will remain mentally colonized if
that happens and so on. So, and and we
have to take the lead in
the space race or at least be a major
participant in the play space race. We
have to be a major player in AI and
semiconductors in manufacturing.
Um we have to spend more of our GDP on
on defense right now. Maybe 5% of of our
GDP on defense for the next 10-20 years
perhaps.
And we have to stop cut we have to cut
down on all these wasteful yojanas.
These things, you know, otherwise all of
these things could haunt us in 2050. We
have to expel all the all the goddamn
foreigners from India
who are squatting on our territory
illegally.
100 million Bangladeshis possibly
I don't know how many lakh cookies. I
don't know how many lakh Pakistanis.
Why are they still on Indian territory?
Why are we feeding them and their
children? Why?
These things need to be addressed
urgently.
Fast snail says, should Hindus despise
Ashoka as much as invaders? Very
controversial topic.
Look, Ashoka did a lot of great stuff,
okay? He unified the entire
subcontinent.
He retook No, he did not. His
grandfather did that. He His grandfather
retook Gandhara from the Yavanas.
But Ashoka,
he
propped up this
he he took this obscure religious sect
called Buddha Dharma
and turned it into a global global
force.
So, should Hindus despise him as much as
as invaders? I'm not sure. I think
Hindus should individually decide uh how
they feel about Ashoka.
I think it should be
um I think it is not my place to
to
tell Hindus what to think about Ashoka.
Hindus should know the facts and decide
individually on their own.
Uh Rarun Rajir says, recent exchange
recent change
in the way Twitter functions or X
functions has revealed that many of the
US and Indian political accounts were
based in Pakistan. No wonder there was
so much hatred towards Indians. But in
other social media,
it's been pushed as everything is
Indians. So, yeah.
Many of these hateful accounts were
spewing hatred towards India and Indians
and Hindus.
Most of these turned out to be based in
Pakistan. So, today if you look at a
Twitter account and if it says South
Asia,
it means it's either Bangladesh or
Pakistan.
Because nobody in India will say will
put their region as South Asia.
But Pakistanis and Bangladeshis want to
hide the fact that they're from Pakistan
or Bangladesh, so they will
you have the choice of either
either setting your location as your
country or your region. And the region
is is if you don't want to choose your
country, you can put your region as
South Asia over here. It should be the
Indian subcontinent, but why would Elon
Musk do that? So, he has put it as South
Asia.
So, a lot of these accounts, hateful
accounts, are based in South Asia, which
means mostly Pakistan or Bangladesh.
And they have created this this big
narrative this anti-India narrative on
social media. And they've been very
successful.
And
you know, this is a game that two can
play, but but India has chosen not to
play the game. The government of India
has not invested in the social media war
at all. We just like sitting ducks. It's
only the citizens who are fighting on
their own.
Right? The government of India has not
has not chosen not to weaponize social
media the way that Pakistanis do, the
Chinese do, the Americans do. We we are
Satyameva Jayate. We will play by
Gandhi's principles, right? That's what
the government of India believes in.
Sad.
Uh okay. R Rahul says, my hypothesis,
there is no singularity if density of an
object crosses a limit, its interaction
with Higgs field becomes weaker to save
space-time. To save space-time.
Okay. Um
So, if your interaction with the Higgs
field is not weak, then does it eat
space-time or destroy space-time? I'm
not sure.
How are you space saving space time?
I I'm just trying to understand. Look.
What's the Higgs field?
What's the Higgs boson? Right? The god
particle.
You all have heard of the god particle,
the god particle.
Let me explain what this thing is.
Is it a god particle?
So, in the 2010s, around that time,
um the Higgs boson was finally
discovered
in the Large Hadron Collider. It's the
one discovery the Large Hadron Collider
made.
Nothing Anything else of significance.
And because of that, Peter Higgs finally
won the Nobel Prize after more than 50
years after he proposed this theory of
the Higgs boson. So, the Higgs boson
is this
particle
that is also a field. So, see, in
quantum field theory, there are no
particles. There's only fields. There is
a universal proton field. There's a
universal electron field. There's a
universal neutron field, and and so on.
So, there are what, 17 fundamental
particles? There are There are some 17
fundamental fields. And what we see as a
particle, a proton, electron, whatever,
these are merely localized excitations
of the field.
Now, there's a Higgs field.
Okay?
And
if a particle interacts strongly
with the Higgs field, then it has more
mass.
If a particle interacts weakly with the
Higgs field, it has less mass.
And some particles don't interact with
the Higgs field. They have no mass. They
are massless particles.
Okay? So, the strong The stronger your
The particle's interaction is with the
Higgs field, the more massive it's going
to be. So, that's why
the proton interacts
more strongly with the Higgs field
compared to the electron. So, you can
see why the proton has more mass than
the electron. So, the Higgs field is
what imbues particles with mass. That's
what the Higgs field is, and that's what
the Higgs boson is. A Higgs boson is a
localized excitation
in the Higgs field.
Now,
okay?
So, now your hypothesis is that if the
density of an object crosses a limit,
its interaction with the Higgs field
becomes weaker to save space time.
So, now that we understand the Higgs
field,
you will see that there is no connection
between the Higgs field and space time.
The Higgs field is a quantum mechanical
phenomenon.
Quantum field theory phenomenon.
And space time is general relativity.
These two don't mix and match.
They don't mix and match.
Quantum mechanics is in incompatible
with general relativity.
No physicist has been able to reconcile
the two theories thus far.
You try, it's going to throw up weird
stuff.
It's going to crash and burn.
Doesn't work. So, um considering what we
just discussed, I'm not sure how
density of an object
See, when we talk about fundamental
particles
at the quantum level, we don't talk
about particle densities. We simply talk
about particle mass, typically in giga
electron volts, in electron volts.
Not even in in in in
in kilograms.
So, we don't talk about particle
densities.
And when we talk about a singularity, a
singularity by definition has infinite
density.
All right? So, yeah.
See, if if you have a hypothesis, it's
it's good to have it, but you need to
formalize it mathematically.
You need to formalize it mathematically.
You have to create toy model or
something and play out the mathematics
with the known physics and see if it
really works.
So, physics is not expressed in terms of
words. Physics is expressed in terms of
equations. That's the only way physics
works.
I can explain to you physics in by using
various kinds of analogies,
but real physics is done with
mathematics and equations.
Pratham Soni says, "Any specific habits
to raise our standards? Admiring you a
lot." Thank you very much. Okay, any
specific habits to raise your standards?
Okay, one habit. One requirement, I
would say.
You want to raise your standards, first
start with the physical body.
If you want to raise your standards, you
have to You should I recommend you
should walk minimum 20 km per week.
Very specific minimum limit I'm giving
you.
You should walk a minimum of 20 km per
week.
Ideally, you should walk more than 30 km
per week.
Is it possible?
20 km per week, 7 days, 7 3s are 21.
It's less than 3 km a day. It's nothing.
You can I can walk 3 km in like 15
minutes, I would say.
Now, maybe 20 minutes.
You can definitely walk 3 km in in half
an hour.
Definitely. Right?
So,
you should be You should do that. That's
one.
Walking
walking 20 km a week should be a minimum
thing you should have. And if possible,
lift weights.
At least two to three times a week, not
more than five, six times a week. Not
more than five times a week.
So, that's another specific habit that
you should have.
Uh what else? Spend a certain amount of
time every day reading.
Maybe half an hour read half an hour a
day. Write half an hour a day, something
or the other.
And there's much more. I mean, I will I
I cannot tell you everything off the top
of my mind, otherwise um
But yeah, these are some of the things
you should do.
This right this this walking habit, how
many of us have it?
That alone can make us way healthier
than what we are right now.
And and yeah. Okay, so I'll I'll I'll
I'll keep it at that at this point in
time. Maybe I should make a video about
list of habits for raising your
standards, perhaps. Yeah.
Okay. Uh Raj Rarun Rajar says, "Even my
remote village is in street view by a
bike guy."
Yeah, India is penetrated. India is
penetrated. There we have it.
Yuvraj Chip says, "If you travel at the
speed of light, the distance shrinks.
How is it possible? Can you please
explain how this phenomenon takes place
in space time?"
You can't travel at the speed of light.
You can't.
You are a massive object. You have a
body, physical body. Uh if you are an
average male, you would weigh about 60,
70 kilos. Yeah?
So, if you have a weight of 70 A mass of
70 kilos, you can't travel at the speed
of light. If you have a mass of even 1
g, you can't travel at the speed of
light. You can't.
Why? Because of special relativity.
The faster you travel,
the more massive you become.
Okay, and that can be
And how do we know this? Because of the
Lore- Lorentz
transformations.
What are the Lorentz transformations?
Very simple. It's something you learn in
the I think first lecture
in special relativity.
Lorentz transformations.
Transformation.
So, what's it look like?
Now, okay, there we have it. So, let's
say gamma is the the factor that comes
in everything.
And because of this factor gamma, you
have
you have uh
length contraction, and you have, you
know, mass which increases as you travel
faster.
So, if you
travel
at relativistic speeds, which are
significant fraction of the speed of
light, your mass increases. So, if you
if you have If you're shooting a bullet
that has a weight of 1 A mass of 1 g,
but if you are shooting it at a
significant percentage of the speed of
light, the mass will be way more than 1
g. The faster it goes, the more massive
it gets.
And you have length contraction. So, if
you have a ruler, let's say it is It has
a length of 1 m,
and you it's traveling at a significant
for percentage of the speed of light,
it's going to shrink.
Right? So, how does it happen? I cannot
explain to you in words. I cannot
explain to you with analogies. I can
only show you the equations, and you
have to You have to understand how the
equations work and how they have been
derived.
There is no other way of explaining it.
The only way to explain this is through
mathematics.
So, look up the Lorentz transformation,
the thing that I just put on the screen.
Try and figure out how it works. And if
you are able to do that, then you will
understand how it works.
Now, Rohan Suneja wants to ask me the
same question multiple times. How did
Scandinavia become so prosperous? Look,
I don't have the answer to this right
now.
I think you asked me two, three times
before in the last two, three live
streams, but I haven't studied this part
of history in detail.
So, I won't be able to tell you how did
Scandinavia become so prosperous. It is
reasonably prosperous. It's not as
prosperous as the United States. It's
not as prosperous as other countries,
but GDP per capita is pretty good,
actually. So, they've been doing a good
job, but how did they do it
specifically? I'm not sure.
So, right now, I can't answer. Sorry.
Feminist Slayer says, "Is it possible to
follow a timetable perfectly?" It is. If
you are a perfectionist person, you can.
But do you want to?
So, you see, when you go to school, you
have a timetable, right? If you go to
school, eighth standard, they will give
you a timetable. First lecture First
period is this, second is this, this so
and so time the period starts, so and so
time it ends, so and so time you have a
20-minute break, then the next four
periods, what time does the school end?
Ding ding ding ding ding, they'll do.
They follow timetable perfectly, mostly,
right? It's possible. As an individual,
you can create a timetable for yourself
for whatever you're doing. You can
follow that also perfectly. The point
is, do you want to do it? See, everybody
is different. Everybody follows
different patterns. Everybody has
different ways of approaching things.
For some people, you need timetables.
For some people, you need time blocking.
For some for other people, you need
systems and so on. So, it's certainly
possible to follow a timetable
perfectly.
Okay.
Raru Raru
says, "Okay. You mentioned Sorry, I
don't know your name. I don't know how
to pronounce pronounce that. Sorry. So,
you mentioned that you have no idea if
we have AI in the army." Just Oh, no.
No, we do.
To some extent, we do. Just wanted to
say that we do have it in the military
as a research and it's used recently.
Trust me. Well, I'm happy. I
See, I don't have sources in Pakistan
and so on, but I know
some people who are associated with the
you know,
connected to the Indian armed forces.
So, there is certainly
some AI in the army.
Yeah.
Some AI.
Uh I'm not sure See, we don't have the
kind of AI the Americans have, okay?
We have some AIs AI systems in the army.
And it will not it will definitely not
be at the level of the Americans.
But it's not like we don't have AI AI in
the armed forces. So, yeah. I agree.
Okay. UMX
Glow la ha ha says,
"I tell people
Macaulay's legacy still shapes our
mindset, but they brush it off as
irrelevant today and claim it doesn't
matter in today's world."
See, people
Most people don't want to think.
For most people, thinking is hard work.
Thinking hurts your mind.
We just want to believe whatever we have
been told to believe, and we want to
live with that.
We don't want too much change in life.
Routine is nice. Life is comfortable. We
want to stay comfortable.
We say we talk about Macaulay's legacy,
then we don't wonder what is Macaulay.
We don't study Macaulay's thing and all
the do the impact analysis of what of
his actions in today's world. And we
have to change our things. Then they'll
say, "No, no, no, no, no. There's no
need to do anything. Irrelevant.
Nothing."
And most people they in India, they are
super sheep-like. They defer to
authority. The authority is your
teachers, your leaders, your your media
personnel, your entertainers, your your
TV news anchors, your favorite
politicians. They all say everything is
good today.
Right? So, people will believe all that.
That's the problem.
Kiran Mori says, "Russia has offered
Su-57 and Su-75 to India."
Well, yes. Um
They they have indeed offered these.
Now, the question is, are they offering
full technology transfer as they are
claiming, or are there some other
conditions that we may not we may have
to look into? And what are the price
points? All of these things will have to
be looked into, but I would say that,
you know, if these things are being
offered,
we should take them.
Swastik Mahesh says, "If Operation
Sindhu continues, will the government
focus on taking some territories of
Pakistan like Sindh merging with India
as said by Shri Rajnath Singh ji?"
Look, the way I see it,
if there is a war, even if it's a
three-day war,
it is pointless unless territory changes
hands.
We're not playing a football game here,
right? 7-3 4-2 or whatever. I destroyed
these many planes. You destroyed You
claim to destroy these many planes. But
I have more, so I I win. That's not how
you fight a war.
The objective of war needs to have There
There needs to be very clear objectives,
political and military objectives.
And the only way to shut the whole world
up
is by taking territory.
So, that's what needs to happen.
The next time there is a conflict with
Pakistan, territory needs to change
hands. Otherwise, you're wasting your
time.
So, I'm glad Mr. Rajnath Singh ji has
said whatever he said, but let's make it
happen, yes?
Okay. Satellite says, "When we say
motivation is bad because it's
temporary, but what if we take that same
motivation recurring systematically? By
the way, thanks for existing." Thank you
so much.
Um
See,
motivation recurring systematically.
Why do I say that motivation I don't say
motivation is bad. I say motivation
doesn't work because, like you say, it's
temporary. What is motivation?
Motivation is an emotion, right? You
watch a YouTube video and watch some guy
gives a very emotional speech with
fantastic epic music. So, you feel all
motivated. Yes, the emotion is there.
After half an hour,
gone.
Where's the motivation? It's gone after
half an hour, right?
But what if you take the same motivation
recurring systematically? So, it means
every half an hour you watch that
speech.
You're going to waste your time, don't
you think?
Watching those speeches every half an
hour, or maybe playing that epic music
every half an hour?
It doesn't work like that.
It doesn't work like that. You have to
create systems.
And you have to follow the systems no
matter what your emotional state is.
Whether you're feeling great, whether
you're feeling low, whether you're
feeling motivated, whether you're
feeling completely deflated, whether
you're feeling strong, whether you're
feeling weak, doesn't matter. You follow
the system. That's what you have to do.
You cannot rely on emotions.
If you have make a system of of It's
like
It's like taking drugs every half an
hour. I mean, imagine how bad that is.
Or it's like drinking coffee every after
every half an hour. Eventually, the
coffee will stop having an effect on
you. Then you will need higher and
higher doses of coffee
or whatever else you're doing.
You see, that's why motivation doesn't
work. It's like a drug.
Follow systems and ignore your emotions.
Transcend your emotions. That's how you
succeed.
Dark Knight says,
"Conquering Adharmic peoples and
civilizations will in the long long term
benefit them themselves
and all of humanity. Being aggressive
against Adharmic civilizations doesn't
contradict our values."
See,
See, one of the ways of looking at our
values is
is that
Ahimsa paramo dharma.
Right?
Ahimsa paramo dharma means Ahimsa,
non-violence is the greatest
objective of dharma.
Now, how do you achieve non-violence?
Tell me.
How do you achieve non-violence?
How do you achieve a state of peace and
non-violence?
You achieve that by destroying all
violent people.
So, to achieve a state of peace and
dharma, you have to first destroy the
Adharmics.
Ahimsa paramo dharma.
So, I I don't think that contradicts our
values, does it?
All right.
VSVS says, "Who do you think is the most
competent Indian PM today to date?"
Prime Minister Modi.
Of all the prime ministers we've had
thus far, Prime Minister Modi is the
most competent one we've had. No
question about it.
Okay. Bak Bal Ki Today says, "What is
Lord's Prayer Stone of Canada? Why is it
weird?" When Lord's See, I don't know
anything about Christianity, okay?
Uh but let me see. What is Lord's Prayer
Stone of Canada? Canada? What's a
Canada?
Lord's Prayer
Stone of Canada.
Are you saying Canada?
It's some kind of rune stone with Lord's
Prayer Swedish runes. Okay, I am not
aware of. Whoa, whoa. What happened?
1 second.
Oh, sorry. I did not put the thing on
the screen. Here we have it. So, Lord's
Prayer Prayer Stone of Canada is a Vava
rune stone slab of bedrock, etc. But
with some Swedish runes, 17th century
Swedish runes. I'm not aware of this, so
won't be able to answer unless I do the
research right now. Not not sure about
it.
Godliness says, "The colonial imprint is
in ascendancy. Netflix and Amazon are
the new tools. English is still the
prime attraction. The future future
looks hazy for our
return, the threshold of no return? Have
we crossed the event horizon?" Hopefully
not.
Hopefully not, but we need to course
correct urgently.
Uh we have various state governments who
are saying that you we are very proud to
announce that we are now making English
language education compulsory in all the
provinces.
If we continue like this, we are doomed.
So, we are close, I would say, to the
point of no return, to the event
horizon. And if we don't course correct
soon, very rapidly in the next
maybe 5 years, we're done.
Fast Snail says, "Despite technological
advances, there's no permanent cure for
cancer. Our priorities messed up, or is
it deliberate?
It's Is Mars more important? Don't mean
to be philosophical."
You know, most likely
a cure various cures for cancer do
exist, but those have been suppressed.
See,
the Western pharmaceutical industry is
all about
it's all about maximizing revenue.
It's not about curing people. It's about
cultivating patients who are recurring
patients for your for their entire
lifetime.
It's it's an exploitative
business model.
You don't cure people.
You turn them into lifelong customers
for your for very for various drugs and
treatments.
So, if someone discovers the the cure to
cancer, that that will have to be
suppressed. Otherwise, you know, it's
the end of the story. How will you make
money then?
So, I am pretty sure that the cure that
a cure various cures to cancer do exist,
but those have been suppressed in the
West. The Russians have come up with a
cancer vaccine that seems to be doing
very well in Russia.
So, maybe now
suddenly, multiple new cures for cancer
will emerge in the West potentially if
the Russians start distributing the the
the
cancer vaccine to the countries. Then
the West will have to now step in and
say that no, you know what, we are
better.
So,
yeah, you're not being philosophical,
you're being practical and the world is
very evil, you see? That's how it works.
Ritwik Pawar says, "Who's the worst PM
India ever had?" Look, now you're trying
to put me in a in a in a spot, okay?
I will tell you who's the best Prime
Minister we had, it's Prime Minister
Modi thus far. Who's the worst? No, no,
no, I am not answering that question.
I am not getting into those
controversies. I've I've I've had enough
controversies for now.
Who's the worst Prime Minister?
I would say
Oh, I don't know. No. No, no, no, no,
no, no. I am not going there.
Ritwik, sorry.
VS VS says, "Do you think India will be
able to redeem itself if you have stable
leadership with reforms?" Absolutely.
Not Not See,
stable leadership is
a necessary condition, but it's not a
sufficient condition.
Just stable leadership with reforms will
not
pull us out pull us in the right
direction. We need
strong visionary leadership which is
also stable.
A leader who is willing to take big
risks
and and make very unpopular choices.
That's what we need. Stable Stability
Anybody can provide stability.
But you need a leader who is not only
able to merely provide stable
leadership, but also very strong
leadership which means doing things that
are unpopular in the short term. That's
what we need. Those sort of reforms.
If we have that, then yeah, anything's
possible.
Kiran Morey says, "Saab
offers jet engine tech to India. Take
it.
Take it.
Pay whatever it takes.
Acquire it."
Right? So, I'm glad it's happening.
Okay.
Okay, we've crossed 3 hours. Okay,
please all of everyone stop taking super
chats because I need to now at some
point in time end this stream. It was
supposed to be a 2-hour stream, it's
already 3 hours. So, yeah, okay.
Ganapathy says,
"Don't agree with Israel, but a pleasure
listening to you." Absolutely, sir, we
don't have to agree on everything.
All right, we can agree to disagree.
At the end of the day, we are in the
same boat and I think overall, we are
going in the same direction. We want to
go in the same direction. We all want
India to do great.
Right? We can disagree on other things
here and there. Whatever, it's fine.
But thank you so much for being
a viewer. I
value you and I appreciate you and all
of you. Thank you.
Naiyutika says, "Mass immigration to the
West is a social experiment based on the
Cloward-Piven strategy and negative
income tax theory of Friedman to enable
basic income."
There are all kinds of social
experiments that are being run in the
West.
I'm not sure about the Cloward-Piven
strategy and
Friedman's negative income tax theory.
I'm not sure about those specific
uh strategies or whatever, but mass
immigration,
I think there's a UN paper on that,
replacement immigration or something.
And that was published uh
quite a while ago.
Let's
Let's see this. Okay?
UN
Oh, there we have it. I think it's I
think Google is listening to me. Look at
that.
Look at that. Look at that. Look at
So,
replacement migration.
When was this published?
The year 2000.
And that is that is being implemented
today.
So, as you can see,
many of these things are not
conspiracies. These are actually
well-thought-out, well-planned-out
things.
So, I'm not sure about the Cloward-Piven
strategy and Friedman's negative income
tax theory, etc.,
but yeah, there seems to be,
you know,
a push towards the direction of
eventually having universal basic
income. That's what Elon Musk keeps
talking about that. So, maybe that will
be rolled out soon
or reasonably soon soon enough in the
West. We'll see.
Rishil K says, "With growing tensions
between the US and China,
Germany and France are doing war
preparations and conscription. Do you
think Western people will be able to go
to war like they did in the Second World
War?"
Um will the West be able to go to war?
Will the Western European nations be
able to go to war like they did in the
Second World War? I think it's very
doubtful.
In the Second World War, during those
times, there was strong there was a
strong sense of national identity
and patriotism and nationalism, whatever
you want to call it.
Today, significant percentages of the
populations of these nations, Western
European nations,
are of foreign origin. They don't give a
damn about the country.
If the country is in a state of war, you
may have a civil war that breaks out in
the country.
So, I don't think the people of the West
will be able to go to war the way they
did in the Second World War.
Now,
why are Germany and France doing war
preparations? Why are they doing
conscription? What What Who do they want
to fight?
What threat do they face? They claim
They claim that Russia is a threat. Is
it a threat?
They're simply warmongering.
Russia has no intention of going and
conquering Western Europe. What absolute
nonsense is this?
So, it is all all this warmongering and
all of this is done at the behest of the
overall overlord of the Western Europe
region, which is the United States.
And if there's a real war situation, I
don't think
uh the people of Western Europe will be
able to go to war. But see, if there's a
war with Russia between NATO and Russia,
it's not going to be a people-to-people
war with trench warfare and all that.
It's going to be a technological war.
And uh
so, you you may not need that sort of,
you know,
conscription and mobilization.
Okay, Godliness says, "Kashmir, Bengal,
Manipur gone.
Districts like Mewat and some in Kerala
are kind of mini Pakistan. North
Northeastern states are completely cut
from the from our civilization. What
next? Delhi?"
See, Kashmir is a gone case almost, you
could say. Yeah, demographically.
Bengal, it seems to be going in that
direction potentially based on what one
hears. I'm not sure.
Manipur is not gone yet, but yeah, if we
continue things the way they are,
Manipur will also be gone.
Manipur still has a significant Hindu
population.
But the way they are being treated, they
are feeling alienated.
They're feeling like the country doesn't
care about them, the government doesn't
care about them. The government cares
about the Kukis and for Christ's issue
more than the the indigenous Manipuris.
It looks like that, right?
So, I don't know, the government of
India needs to get its act together.
We need to evict all illegal
infiltrators from India, whether it is
Manipur, whether it is
Assam, whether it is
whatever part of the country.
Evict all illegal infiltrators
immediately.
Next 2-3 years.
That's what needs to happen.
Yeah, so there's a there's a
urgent need for these things to happen.
Jibanam Priya Priyadarshi says, "Is
India follow Is India allowing private
players in nuclear energy sector safe?
Is it state-owned in China?"
It is state-owned in China and Russia
mostly, why? What if foreign private
players misuse it? So, I think we need
to set the rules of the game.
Allow Let's say we allow private
players, but we can decide what kind of
private players are allowed.
Will we allow foreign private players in
India in the nuclear energy sector? Or
will we allow only Indians?
Because if we allow foreign foreign
players, then you know, there is there
is the very high chance of infiltration
of this very sensitive sector. So, it's
all
going to depend on the rules of the game
that the government establishes.
Um
So, I am okay with private players as as
long as we have very stringent security
uh standards and we ensure that the
private players are Indian.
And if we allow foreign private players,
we need to be very clear about the
about safeguarding
various things.
About ensuring there is no espionage,
there is no infiltration. We get the
technology that we need,
but we don't allow access to the to our
state secrets and all that. So, it has
to be done very, very carefully.
Okay, Aditya Saik says, "Explain about
Attila the Hun. Why is he demonized?"
Attila the Hun.
Well, he's demonized because he was not
white.
Attila came from the East.
He was a Hun.
See, at the same time when the Huns were
trying to invade India during uh
the time of the Gupta Empire,
at that same time, the the Huns were
trying to invade Rome.
And the Huns, they came from the East.
They came from They originated
in the region where you today have
Mongolia.
So, they were not white people. They
were Easterners.
So, when Easterners come and attack
Europe, they're obviously evil, right?
How can a non-white people try to attack
Europe? How can they do that? Europeans
are superior, white people are superior.
So, that's why he's demonized. And he
was very successful.
He was very successful.
You know what he did?
He came to Europe with elephants.
He crossed mountains on with elephants.
The Romans were shocked out of their
wits.
So, So why he's demonized because he was
very naughty.
The major naughtiness was not being
white.
Minimalist Mavericks is what's with this
OnlyFans body count culture? Indian
girls obsession with Korean and American
boys is Is this brain rot created by
various three-letter agencies? Oh, most
likely it is.
Most likely this brain rot is is is is
engineered.
Has been engineered by various
three-letter agencies. OnlyFans is this
disgusting thing
uh that is
now mainstream part of Western culture.
Uh I suppose it may be accessible in
India, too.
Then you have body count culture. Once
again,
degeneracy.
Then Indian girls obsession with Korean
boys. I mean,
these Korean boy bands, if you look at
those those singers, first of all, you
don't know what what they're singing.
It's a foreign language that you don't
understand. Secondly, you can't tell the
person's gender, whether it's boy or
girl or
What on earth is this boy band nonsense?
Korean boy bands and all.
So it's just, you know, designed to do
rot everyone's brains.
UMX Glo hahaha says,
We were supposed to get
AMA episode this week.
Ask me anything episode this week. So
what am I doing right now?
What am I doing right now?
Is this not an ask-me-anything episode?
What is this? What am I doing right now?
I have been doing this for the past 3
hours and 10 minutes.
You all have been asking me anything,
right?
I'm not sure what you're complaining
about, sir.
Mama Bucket VFX says, "How do you stand
firm
and always speak from pure
self-perception and self-validation
without bending to others perception or
needing external vali- validation?
Thanks."
I
I don't know. Just be yourself, I
suppose.
Be yourself. Don't try to please others.
I think people pleasing is a tendency
that everybody has to some extent.
Um and you have to train yourself to not
do that, I suppose.
Be yourself.
Uh be authentic. Be who you Be who you
are. See, if I do a live stream for 3
hours, I can't act, right?
Uh there are plenty of people on YouTube
who act, who pretend to be something
that they are not.
But they do it because they read from
scripts.
Right? They make these recorded videos
in which they
talk speak about various topics that
typically get the get the material from
ChatGPT,
and then they create have ChatGPT write
a script for them, and then they read
out the script from a teleprompter, so
it looks like they're being very
natural, etc., but they're actually
being parrots. That's what news readers
do.
Like news readers on various big news
channels, they typically read from
teleprompters, but it looks like they're
being very natural.
But you ask them to do a live stream,
live telecast, and speak spontaneously,
they're going to fumble, mumble, and and
mess up.
So
if you do things live, then you have no
option but to be completely authentic
and completely who you are, because you
can't pretend to be something fake for 3
hours, 2 hours, whatever.
So that's what I do, and that's why I
always do everything live.
And how do I do it? I don't know. I'm
I'm just being myself.
I don't know. I
I don't know if there's any secret to
it.
The secret is very simple. Don't lie.
Don't pretend to be something you're
not. Just be yourself. Whether it is
good, whether it's bad, whatever it is,
be authentic. That's all.
All right. Um
Jagjit Middha says, "In the Sri Lankan
Civil War, uh RAW's role is also is
often highlighted, but CIA, ISI, and
other roles are rarely discussed. Can
you explain how various foreign agencies
shaped the conflict and their shifting
interests?"
See, I'll tell you what.
We are told that um the LTTE was this
Hindu organization, right?
And they came up with these tactics like
suicide bombing and and and cyanide
capsules and whatever. Terrorism, etc.
But what you're not told is that the
leader of the LTTE, Velupillai
Velupillai Prabhakaran, was a converted
Christian.
His entire family was Christian.
And they were
And there was this this Nordic country,
okay? I think it was Norway that was
deeply deeply entrenched
into this LTTE affair, okay?
Norway LTTE.
Norway.
The Norwegians.
Yeah, they claimed to be peace
facilitators, etc.
Right? Norway.
And See, Norway is, as we know, it's a
vassal of the US.
And the Norwegians So so you see,
when it comes to these agencies like the
CIA, etc., they will not get involved
directly. They will get involved through
intermediaries.
So Norway was the intermediary.
And uh yeah, they were the facilitators,
they were the intermediaries, and they
were apparently in the peace process,
etc.
Involved in the peace process for more
than a decade.
So that's what I can tell you. I'm not
I've not studied this this in detail. I
don't know exactly specifically how the
CIA, ISI, etc., they they shaped the
conflict, their shifting interests.
Overall,
uh India was drawn into the conflict,
and India did not do a good job at that.
IPKF was not given a proper
The the entire thing was botched.
See, when you send a peacekeeping force,
you it's supposed to have a very clear
time-bound military objective or a set
of military objectives.
Um When you send a professional armed
force to do something, it has to have
time-bound military objectives, clear
military objectives, missions.
But the IPKF was sent as a police force,
which led to a complete disaster and
fiasco.
Uh so that's what happened. It's It's
not the fault of the Indian Army. It's
the fault of the Indian political
leadership of the time, who messed up so
badly.
Um and of course, other agencies would
be involved, but what the details are,
I'm not quite sure. What I know about is
the role of the Norwegians, who acted as
intermediaries of the
of the larger power.
Uh UMX Glo hahaha says, "What state are
you from?"
How does it matter?
I think you can look it up.
I can You can look it up what my
background is.
What my family lineage is. I think it's
very easy to find out what what state I
could be from, right? Come on.
Okay.
Maharana says, "What Which ancient idea
feels most modern now?"
Which ancient idea feels most modern
now?
I don't know.
Ancient ideas, modern ideas. I live in
both worlds. Which ancient ideas feel
most modern?
That's an interesting question. I don't
know.
I think some ideas are timeless, aren't
they?
Some ideas are timeless. I think uh
What what do we mean by modern, first of
all?
Um
Modern. What What do we mean by modern?
Something that's
Do we mean technologically? Do we mean
it's cool? Do we mean it's something
else?
I'm not sure. I'm not sure. Maybe I
don't have an answer to the question.
Okay. Raju Raju Rarun Rajar says,
"Security problems of Street View. It's
infiltrated a lot more places in India
compared to others." See, security
problems of Street View is that if you
are a terrorist from Pakistan,
and you want to instead of coming to
India and doing your doing
reconnaissance, if you want to just if
you want to target some city in India,
then you can simply go to Street View
and look at the map and spend a few
hours understanding the topol-
topography of the street, the kind of
shops you have, and so on, and you can
do a good job without every without ever
setting foot in a city. So that's a
straightforward security problem of
Street View.
And a lot of the shops, establishments
are clearly visible. So in case uh you
you know,
someone wants to do a theft in your
shop, then I suppose they can find out
ways of doing it from Street View, etc.
So, that's the deal.
UMX Glo hahaha says, "Do you smoke and
drink occasionally?" Listen, I'm not
answering these questions. It It It has
no
um
It doesn't provide any value
to the audience, and these are personal
questions. So I will not answer either
yes or no. It's none of anyone's
business. I don't have any It's none of
my business asking you whether you
smoke, drink, or do whatever.
And the same goes the other way. So
there we have it.
Ohm Sushant Bhardwaj, well, thank you
very much, sir. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Ritik Pawar says, "Is Venezuela on the
brink of collapsing?" Maybe.
See, Trump has said that he he has
declared unilaterally that the airspace
over Venezuela is closed now.
Yeah? I mean, is it legal?
According to international law, is it
allowed what he just did
yesterday?
Where is the United Nations? What are
they doing?
So, the US seems to be on the brink of
doing something in when Venezuela. Maybe
it will collapse. It looks like that.
Yeah.
Suga says, "I want strength to follow
and protect my Dharma. For that, I need
enough protein. Chicken cheap way for me
in to hit my intake."
Rigveda and Atharvaveda don't ban
chicken, but Garuda Garuda
Purana have punishment for it. What to
do?
The Rigveda is the answer to your
questions. It is the foundational text
of our culture and civilization.
If the Rigveda says there is nothing
wrong with it, please go ahead and do
it.
That's your answer.
Don't overcomplicate things.
Consult the Rigveda.
If it's If the Rigveda is fine with it,
you can do it. All right, there we have
it.
Snag says, "Russia-Ukraine, is this a
war of attrition?
All alone?
It's
It's kind of become a war of attrition,
right? Slow war, frozen conflict,
never-ending warfare.
That sort of thing, but there's a reason
for it. Why is Russia okay with the war
going on for years now, when they have
been in a position for the longest time
to flatten Ukraine if they wanted to?
They have the firepower to flatten much
bigger much more powerful countries.
After all, the Germans said that the
Russians are the the biggest danger for
Western Europe, right? Which means that
the Germans are claiming that Russia has
is powerful enough to to defeat Western
Europe.
Then, why is Russia stuck in Ukraine?
There's a reason for it. Russia is
allowing this war to meander
so that it drains the resources of the
West, especially Europe. That's why.
Right?
Anand
Anant
Bharatvarsha says, "Many foreign writers
claim the Ashvamedha ended with a queen
with a queen mating with the horse. Is
this true or a distortion of our of our
culture?"
See, you will find these claims in
English translations.
And not all English translations, some
So, it most likely indicates that this
is that's a distortion.
It's it's it it indicates that the
translator has taken liberties with his
translation of the original Sanskrit.
So, to set these these these claims to
rest, what you have to do
is take to is take the time to to learn
Sanskrit and then read the original.
Then, you will know for sure what the
deal is. Okay? It's always translations
into English or European languages that
raise these issues. It's never
translations into Indian languages from
Sanskrit that make such claims. So,
that's that should indicate something to
you.
Sankar Chillukuri says, "AI advancement,
will that lead to communism? Recently,
New York
recent mayor election populism proved to
be popular." Now, that has nothing to do
with AI advancement.
That is because of a
it's a societal shift.
Because
the average person in the US now
now has more sympathies towards
socialism. That's why you had the
election of Mondani.
Right?
Uh Gad Saad would call it suicidal
empathy or whatever. So, I don't think
it's because of AI whatsoever. It's
because of the
the cultural shift in American society.
The education system has
put this virus in their heads. This
sympathy for socialism, which is by the
standards of nose-diving in the US.
Luton Roshan says,
"O Arya,
West
West seems to be very superior to us.
Uh right now, is there anything or tech
that we have now and is superior to the
West apart from culture, at least a
thing? No."
Ask yourselves.
What does India produce
that the world wants or needs?
What?
Ask yourselves this question honestly.
I'm not asking about India's potential.
I'm asking about what is India doing
right now.
Do we have something that is superior to
the rest of the world apart from
culture?
That's a very hard question to answer
because there's no good answer to it.
Right now, we are nowhere superior to
anybody anywhere.
To the West at least.
That's the truth.
And that needs to change.
Because we have the potential to be the
best.
But all we do is slogan slogan slogan
slogan Vishwaguru Vishwaguru Vishwaguru
superpower superpower.
Slogans will take us nowhere.
Things have to change.
Siddharth Sharma says, "Are you
following news about the interstellar
object 3I Atlas? There are 13 anomalies
presented by Professor Avi Loeb. What do
you think about it?"
See,
Professor Avi Avi Loeb is
a scientist with a very solid reputation
and
a very credible background.
So, if he says something, you would take
him seriously.
Now, when we look at the data given by
given out by NASA
and official space agencies, they will
tell you that everything is fine with AI
3I Atlas.
Nothing anom- anomalous at all.
But Avi Loeb says that there are
anomalies.
So,
if
there are anomalies
in the way this object is behaving,
then it's being covered up by NASA et
cetera.
So, there are two possibilities. Either
NASA is covering up the anomalies
and saying everything is fine even
though it's not,
or Avi Loeb is over representing what's
happening. Those are the two
possibilities. Now, I have don't have a
telescope here with which I can observe
what's happening. I can only rely on
information that is second-hand to me.
So, I have the choice of either
believing NASA or believing Avi Loeb.
I'm not quite sure where to go right
now.
So, can't say.
I think the only way we'll find out if
something is really
really anomalous is if 3I Atlas makes a
U-turn and comes to Earth and then says,
"Hi, we are here. We come in peace."
Otherwise, can't say.
But yeah, it's it's
it's a very exciting time that we have
these interstellar objects that are
that are entering our solar system.
And it would be nice to see real-time
live coverage of what's happening, but
we don't have it.
Maharana says, "What Which unforeseen
experiment most profoundly shaped
history, not by intention, but by
consequence?"
What?
Which unforeseen experiment
Which unforeseen experiment most
profoundly reshaped history?
I think one of the most
The printing press by Gutenberg.
Yeah, it suddenly brought literacy to
the West.
I mean, how come India did not invent
the printing press?
What was wrong with our people we did
not invent the printing press?
Seriously, is it something very
high-tech?
So, that's one thing that, you know,
that brought very rapid literacy to the
West and it profoundly reshaped history.
And that probably was not the intention
of Gutenberg.
He only wanted to print Bibles, but it
had a very different effect. So, yeah,
maybe that.
Apoorva Aditya says, "No matter how much
I try, I can't I just can't bother
attending classes in college. I can't
find my interest. I'm losing interest in
everything. What can I do?"
Look, you're not losing interest in
everything. You're losing interest in
everything that's being forced upon you.
You clearly have interests, but those
are not in line with what you are
expected to do.
So, what can you do?
Well, you have tough choices in front of
you, sir.
You can either force yourself to attend
your classes and get your degree and
then go and do a job that you don't
like,
or whatever it is that interests you,
you can try and make a make a career out
of that,
which is
a hard path,
which is the path of entrepreneurship or
or being an artist or something.
Whatever it is, I don't know what your
path is.
So, you have these two choices. One is
do the do do what is expected. Be
unhappy in life.
Go attend classes even though you can't
find anything interesting. Go pass your
exams with whatever grades you can even
though it's not interesting to you.
Then, go apply for a job and then do a
job 9:00 to 5:00 or whatever and
whatever.
That's one path. The other path is
whatever you actually find interesting
because clearly there'll be something
you find interesting in life.
It's not like
you have no interest in anything at all.
There will be things that you find
interesting, that you'll be passionate
about. But can you make a career out of
that?
That's the question that you have. If
you can do it, you'll be happy.
Otherwise, you have to make a compromise
in life and
go along the path
that is expected.
Right? So, you have to find your way in
life. You are at at this crossroads
right now.
Yeah.
All right, sir. I hope you make the
right choices and get what you want.
All the best, Apoorva.
Vipul
Vipul Pawar, thank you very much, sir.
Thank you.
Hey, what kind of language is this? Yes,
you cannot use such language on my
channel. This is good channel.
You can't use Russian slang terminology
here. It's very bad, sir. You can't do
this.
Okay.
In Alaska meet, I realized that only the
US, Russia, and France have a
presidential plane, which is indigenous.
Even she uses Boeing. Isn't it
interesting? What's my detailed opinion?
That's a very interesting observation.
The Americans have Boeing or whatever.
That's an American
company.
The Russians have their own aircraft
manufacturing companies like like
Yakovlev and Tupolev and
many others, I suppose. So, President
Putin would probably fly in one of those
indigenous planes.
France
What aircraft does Mr. Macron use?
Uh
Macron
uh
aircraft
Let's see.
Cote
d'Ivoire Unite
Oh, it must be Airbus, right? It must be
an Airbus.
Okay, it's an Airbus. So, once again,
it's French. Oh, yes, of course, the
French have Airbus.
So, yeah, so so these three countries,
their heads of state have indigenous
aircraft. Mm, Xi Jinping has to use
Boeings and uh
Prime Minister Modi probably uses Boeing
aircraft, right?
That's very interesting. So, you know
the Chinese will soon have
an indigenously
developed aircraft for their president
because they are working very hard. They
already have certain airliners,
jetliners that they
they've developed at home. And they are
trying to bring them up to international
standards. But we in India don't have
any civilian aircraft
manufacturing program.
Maybe in 20 years we'll start something
and try to copy what others are doing.
We are always behind. India is a nation
that lacks ambition. Our leaders lack
ambition. That's the problem that I see
all the time.
Right? We are we are big on slogans.
But we lack ambition, seriously.
The Chinese, when they were at our GDP,
they were 100 times more ambitious than
we are today.
Sad.
Vipul Bohra says, is there any
scientific basis for the idea that
consciousness allows the universe to
become self-aware? There is no
scientific basis to this idea.
None whatsoever.
Why do I say this?
Because consciousness is not a
scientific concept.
Why do I say that?
See, we are drilling down to first
principles.
First, I'm saying there is no scientific
basis to this idea that consciousness
allows the universe to become
self-aware.
Now, why am I saying this?
Because there is
because
consciousness the the concept of
consciousness is not a scientific
concept. Now, why do I say it's not a
scientific concept?
We're drilling drilling down further.
Because science doesn't have a
definition of consciousness.
Now, what do I mean by that? It means
that there is no definition of
consciousness from a neuroscience
perspective. There is no definition of
consciousness from
a physics perspective from from from
from a quantum mechanical perspective
from a thermodynamic perspective from a
general relativity perspective from
information theory perspective.
There is no definition of consciousness
from a
biochemistry perspective.
There is no scientific definition of
consciousness. We can't even define
thing.
Then how can you talk about scientific
basis for any ideas of consciousness?
You see there?
That's the issue.
We don't have a definition of
consciousness. We know it exists.
We know it exists. The moment we see we
know yeah, that's conscious. We know it.
But we can't define it. That's the big
problem.
So, and and all these theories about,
you know
the universe is self-aware. That's
called
cosmopsychism.
That's a philosophical concept. It's not
a scientific concept. Because
consciousness doesn't have a scientific
definition.
Okay, VS VS says, I don't learn
geopolitics, geopolitics learn me. Child
of the
Uh well, thank you so much, sir, for the
very nice thing
for the very nice compliment. Thank you
so much. I appreciate it very much.
Thank you.
Okay, Divine Tiger says, what happened
to Sanyogita ji after Samrat
Prithviraj's death?
I don't know.
There are some versions that say that
she met a very evil fate at the hands of
the Turks.
Some other accounts don't make any
mention of Sanyogita what happened to
her.
So, I I don't know for sure.
I don't want to think too much about it,
actually.
Yeah.
Don't know for sure.
Okay, right arm chuck.
Right arm chuck chuck.
No, chuck is the elbow, right? Elbow.
Okay. How can we be prepared for the
future with AI?
Become AI native. Learn everything about
AI. Learn how to use AI.
As an individual, as a nation
as an individual, you learn AI, right?
You learn how to use AI, how to talk to
AI, how to get AI to do stuff for you,
how to prompt it properly.
You learn what are the different models,
what are their capabilities, which is
the best for whatever you're doing and
so on and so forth. That's what you do.
That's how you become prepared for the
future for AI with AI.
You learn how to use it in your job. You
learn how to use it in your industry, in
your business. You stay two steps ahead
by trying to anticipate how it's going
to affect or disrupt your industry, your
job, your business or whatever. That's
how you prepare for AI. You have to
always be prepared. You have to always
try and stay a couple of steps ahead.
You just always try and
try and anticipate what's happening.
That's how you stay prepared for the
future with AI.
And you should also think about how it's
going to affect the future generations
and how you can prepare your kids for
that in case you have kids.
These are the sort of things you do to
prepare for the future with AI. If
you're a nation, you invest in AI and
you set the terms so that you can
build the future, the kind of future
that AI is going to generate for us.
Okay, Ashutosh
Kasal kar says, your thoughts on Nilesh
Oak's dating Nilesh Oak ji's dating of
Ramayan and Mahabharat. Well, I haven't
studied that, so I can't say.
I haven't studied that.
I know Nilesh Oak ji. I met him
recently. Very nice guy.
Very nice gentleman. Very learned
person.
But I haven't studied um his research.
He's got multiple books on these
subjects. I haven't read any of those,
so I can't say, right?
Um unless I study in detail, I cannot
make any pronouncements whether it's
right, bad, good or bad, fantastic,
terrible. Can't say. Can't say. I
haven't studied.
Uh Sugas Sugas says, what happens to the
soul
according to Dharma after death?
According to Dharma
after death death, the soul goes to a
resting place for a while. It recovers.
And then it transmigrates to a new body.
And starts the process again.
And then the process goes on and on and
on until you detach the the soul
detaches itself from the
consequences of karma and by that it by
doing so it can transcend the cycle of
life and death and rebirth.
That's what happens to the soul after
Dharma after death according to Dharma.
Okay, Divnur Singh says,
what's the reason Indians become good
citizens under authority more than
others? Why do major revolutions
like French, American Revolution, etc.
never come from India?
See, Indians come from the most mature
civilization, the oldest civilization.
And as such, Indians lived under law and
order longer than any other society on
the planet.
So, it's in our DNA
that we want to be good citizens. We
want to live
in an orderly fashion. If there is law
and order, we want to abide by that.
The French, the the the English, etc.
They come from not really from
civilization. They come from empire.
They've never lived under a proper
civilization.
What you call Western civilization is
actually Western empire today.
Civilization is different from empire.
So
so that's why it's it's
it's more natural. See
why do the Indian police forces
You look at the compare the Indian
police force with the French police
force. If you go to France, if you go to
the streets of Paris
you see the French cops.
What do they look like?
They look like commandos. They are
well-built. They have these automatic
weapons.
They look like they're ready to fight a
battle, fight a war.
They can lead an invasion if they want
to. Have you seen Indian cops? What do
they look like?
Very different, right?
It's because in France, you need that
sort of cop to control the population.
The population is
the population is capable of such
violence. The same
applies to the US.
Walk around New York City.
Look at the cops.
Cops everywhere. Cops ready to shoot if
required, anytime.
Now, walk around any major Indian city.
What do the cops look like?
Very different, right?
The cops know in India that no one's
going to resort to
large-scale violence. Indians don't do
that. Indians are far too civilized. The
Westerners have just been tamed
from their status as barbarians. And
that's why you have this major
difference.
Right? And that's why you don't have
such revolutions in India because even
if a if if a kingdom or
dynasty falls, something else rises up
in its place and you have the same
system that continues, the dharmic
system until now.
Okay.
Russia offered jet engine technology
with fighter jet. I don't know.
Not sure. Did it?
I think
jet engine technology may or may not be
offered. I think the fighter jet
technology is being offered. Maybe we'll
have to negotiate separately for jet
engine technology.
As far as I have seen, they have they
have not offered jet engine tech along
with the fighter jet, the Su-57.
That may be on the cards if we negotiate
appropriately.
But the French are going ahead with us
with this joint um
uh project for a new jet engine. Safran
is the French company that's going ahead
with this with us for this, and that
will give rise to a new jet engine. All
right.
Achintya Anand says, "During peak of the
river flow, I read somewhere that the
Ganga plains were very large marshlands
and hence less populated. I haven't read
this."
I haven't.
I'm not aware of any such thing that the
Ganga plains were very large marshlands
at the time.
As far as I know, the Ganga plains were
the where the Ganga plains are. Maybe
the course may be somewhat different,
but I have not read about this marshland
theory.
All right, that brings me to the end
finally
of the super chats.
It's been very long time, yes?
Almost 4 hours. Good gods.
I had not expected
it would take almost 3 and 1/2 hours.
All right.
Okay, there's one Okay, there's more
super chats. Listen, please do not take
any more super chats. I'm ending this
live stream in 5 minutes.
So, there are two right now. I will just
take two and then then I have to end it.
Otherwise, it's going to end up as an
8-hour live stream and I
not for today. So, uh Suga says, "Do you
think Buddhism is part of Sanatana
Dharma or not?" It is one of the
aspects of Dharma. It is one of the
valid philosophical schools of thought
or philosophical paths that are
part of what we call the Dharmic
umbrella. So, yes, it is.
And despite my request, people are
taking more super chats.
Okay.
Devnoor Singh says, "Yahweh, the Old
Testament God, was one of the few gods,
but his followers prevailed. Yahweh
ordered genocides. He was a war god.
How did monotheism come out of that?"
Look, Devnoor Singh ji,
I'm not any kind of expert
in Judaism, in Christianity, in Yahweh,
all that.
I don't know how many See, I I'm aware
that
Yahweh was one of the
gods, one of the gods in the original
form of Judaism. The original oldest
known Judaism was not a monotheistic
religion. But then
Yahweh prevailed or his followers
prevailed and that's how it went.
Uh I don't know about the genocides. I
don't know about the war god, etc.
aspect and all that.
And uh
but we know that eventually Juda-
Judaism becomes this monotheistic
religion and the other Abrahamic
religions
essentially branch out from Judaism.
First Christianity and then Islam.
That's what I can tell you. Beyond that,
I'm not aware of the genocide aspect.
I've not read their sacred texts,
whatever they may contain. So, I can't
say anything about that.
VSBS says, "I'm confident that we will
reclaim our former glory again. Jai
Hind." I am very confident, too.
Uh but my thing is that I want to see it
happen in my lifetime. That's all.
I know it'll happen.
So, yeah. I'm I'm I completely agree
with you. Jai Hind indeed.
Uh Minimalist Maverick says, "Is it
possible
US is making a virus to the top 20 tier
one humans so my bottom 80% perish? Is
it possible to create such viruses or
more advanced?" Look, I don't know what
the US is doing.
Is it theoretically possible to create
such viruses? It is.
It is.
Is the US doing it? I have no idea. Is
it possible some nation X nation Y
nation Z nation be doing it? It is
possible.
Yeah. I think the technology now exists
for doing such things.
Yeah.
Divine Tiger says, "I want to learn
lethal martial arts when I'm 30 years
old." So,
you're not 70, right?
It's fine. You can learn.
Go ahead and learn. No one's stopping
you.
You'll need to, you know,
get in physical shape for that, but at
the age of 30, you certainly can do
that. Why not? Go ahead and do it.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. That brings me
to the end, very much to the end of
today's live stream. So, thank you so
much, everybody.
Almost 4 hours this session.
And once again, we have more super
chats. Now, what should I do about this?
Okay, I will take one last super chat
and this is the end.
Vipul Pawar, your super chat is the last
one I'll take today. Does physics
explain why only the 5% Does
physics explain
only the 5% we can perceive?
Okay. Let me try to unpack what Vipul
Pawar is saying.
If we observe the universe, we see
stars, galaxies, nebulas, and what not,
gas clouds. So, you see all these points
of light in the sky, in the night sky.
And if you add all of that mass
together,
it makes up about 5% of the actual mass
of the universe. So, everything we can
see, it's just 5% roughly of the mass of
the universe, mass energy of the
universe.
About 25% roughly is dark energy,
which is some kind of particle or family
of particles,
and then about 70% is dark energy. 25%
is dark matter and 75% is dark energy,
roughly 75% and we don't even know what
that is, but it's something that seems
to be causing the accelerating expansion
of the universe.
So, we only unders- we are able to only
see 5% of the universe's mass energy.
And of what we see, those five that 5%,
we have a rudimentary understanding of
how it works. Does physics explain
everything about the 5% we can observe?
No. No. No. No.
There's a lot we still don't understand.
Okay?
So, we understand essentially next to
nothing of the universe. That's the
truth.
Despite all of our physics and
technology and all that.
So, yeah, that's the answer, sir. And
Ankita ji, thank you very much, ma'am. I
really appreciate
your contribution. Thank you so much,
ma'am. Thank you.
And with that, I will now finally end
this live stream. So, thank you so much.
It was wonderful. I really enjoyed this.
I took way more questions than I had
expected to take, but thank you so much.
I It is a privilege that I have so many
questions that I get to field. Others
don't get to do that. So, thank you so
much, everyone.
And I look forward to
seeing you all
next week in next week's live streams.
Take care, everyone. Keep learning, keep
asking questions, keep raising your
standards, and I'll see you very soon.
Take care. Bye-bye.